<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A iust reproof to Haberdashers-Hall: or, An epistle writ by Lieut. Colonel John Lilburn, July 30. 1651. to four of the commissioners at Haberdashers Hall, viz. Mr James Russell, M. Edward Winsloe, M William Mellins, and M. Arthur Squib, wherein is set forth their unjust and unrighteous dealing in severall cases; with the relations of the said John Lilburn, and their captiving their understandings to the tyrannical will of Sir Arthur Haslerigge, who hath most unjustly endeavoured a long time together, the exterpation of the family of the said John Lilburn.</title>
            <author>Lilburne, John, 1614?-1657.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1651</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 147 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A88209</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L2127</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E638_12</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R206637</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99865756</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99865756</idno>
            <idno type="VID">165914</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A88209)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 165914)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 98:E638[12])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A iust reproof to Haberdashers-Hall: or, An epistle writ by Lieut. Colonel John Lilburn, July 30. 1651. to four of the commissioners at Haberdashers Hall, viz. Mr James Russell, M. Edward Winsloe, M William Mellins, and M. Arthur Squib, wherein is set forth their unjust and unrighteous dealing in severall cases; with the relations of the said John Lilburn, and their captiving their understandings to the tyrannical will of Sir Arthur Haslerigge, who hath most unjustly endeavoured a long time together, the exterpation of the family of the said John Lilburn.</title>
                  <author>Lilburne, John, 1614?-1657.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>40 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1651]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "August".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Commonwealth and Protectorate, 1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:165914:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A IUST REPROOF TO Haberdaſhers-Hall: OR, An Epiſtle writ by Lieu<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Colonel <hi>John Lilburn,</hi> July 30. 1651. to four of the Commiſſioners at <hi>Haberdaſhers Hall,</hi> viz. Mr. <hi>James Ruſſel,</hi> M. <hi>Edward Winſloe,</hi> M <hi>William Mollins,</hi> and M. <hi>Arthur Squib,</hi> wherein is ſet forth their unjuſt and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteous dealing in ſeverall Caſes; with the relations of the ſaid <hi>John Lilburn,</hi> and their Captiving their underſtandings to the Tyrannical will of Sir <hi>Arthur Haſlerigge,</hi> who hath moſt unjuſtly endeavoured a long time together, the exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation of the Family of the ſaid <hi>John Lilburn.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Iſai 29.20, 21.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>For the terrible one is brought to nought, and the Scorner is conſumed, and all that watch for iniquity are cut off.</p>
                  <p>That make a man an offender for a word, and lay a ſnare for him that reproveth in the gate, and turn aſide the juſt for a thing of nought.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <opener>
               <salute>GENTLEMEN,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>MY ſerious eyeing and beholding for divers months together, your moſt unjuſt, partial, and viſible combining way of proceedings a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſome of my nigheſt relations, hath filled me with ſo much deteſtation and indignation againſt your injuſtice, that my heart hath even b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>end within me, and I have with my ſelf had much ado to forbear thus long to ſpeak more plainly to you by my pen, then was ſafe for me to do at your barre (although I have there, as you all very well know, been very free.) But yet to avoyd if it were poſſible, by all rational and ingenuous
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:165914:2"/>men, to be judged turbulent, and irrational. I have rather bridled my paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and indignation, and in a quiet, ſober and moderate way, endeavour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Petitions to the Parliament to eaſe and redreſs the grievances of my ſelf and my relations: but ſome of you with violence, reproaches, and much falſhoods interpoſing to hinder our juſt expected remedy (the particulars of which, by and by I ſhall more fully <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>int unto you) which hath had too great an influence to retard our juſt proceedings: ſo that although my ſelf, and others have done what in us lyes, for divers days by-paſt, to get two pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titions full of juſtice and truth read againſt you, yet cannot: and although you your ſelves directed, and bid me petition againſt you, yet finding that you are to the purpoſe netled at my putting in execution your own deſires, and withall behinde my back to the purpoſe reproach me, and do what in you lies to bereave me of all ordinary and legal means to help my ſelf, and my relations, and thereby force me to betake my ſelf to extraordinary, which is my pen, my laſt and unwilling refuge. In the name, ſtrength, and power of the Lord God Almighty, have at you, and if, I periſh, I periſh: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore before I come to the main combat, give me leave to ſend out theſe For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lornes.</p>
            <p>Firſt, That I plead againſt Sir <hi>Arthur Haſlerigge</hi> (a man unto whom, as to me by your actions you ſeem to have ſold your ſelves to be his ſlaves, and vaſſals in all caſes whatever) who I do over, hath endeavoured for theſe ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral years together, the extirpation and total deſtruction of my whole Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, and al thoſe in the County where they live that have wiſht them wel, and that for no other cauſe but for their honeſty and integrity, and becauſe they will not be his profeſſed ſlaves as other people are, all which I ſhall to you and the world endeavor to demonſtrate thus;</p>
            <p>Firſt my Father <hi>Richard Lilburn,</hi> and my Unkle, <hi>George Lilburn,</hi> Eſquires, with all their ſons, have been well affected to the Parliament, and all of them that have been fit for ſouldiers, freely and faithfully adventured their lives for the Parliament, without ſpot on blemiſh, ſave my unfortunate youngeſt brother, <hi>Henry Lilburn,</hi> who yet viſibly was honeſt enough in the eies of his chief Commanders, till he came under the command of Sir <hi>Arthur Haſelrig;</hi> and my Father and Uncle in the Kings time before the Parliament, were the onely two Gentlemen in all the County of <hi>Durham</hi> that ever I could hear of, that durſt oppoſe the Kings Will and Pleaſure in the point of ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>money; and the Biſhop of <hi>Durham</hi> and his under Prieſts called Deans and Chapters will and pleaſure, in point of innovations; and when the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment came with all their ſtrength adhered to them, and were not willing to be rid upon, nor implicitly led againſt their underſtandings by the power of any great ones whatſoever, that under the Parliament had the chief Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of the County of <hi>Durham,</hi> it being a Baſtard as it were to all the Counties of the Nation: having yet never enjoyed that right and privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge to ſend either Knights or Burgeſſes to Parliament, to repreſent it or ſpeak for it, and therefore was ſubject always to have ſome great one or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to domineer over it: And upon the late conteſt betwixt the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Army, my eldeſt brother Col. <hi>Robert Lilburn,</hi> was thought the fitteſt by the chief Officers of the Army, to be ſent down into his own
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:165914:2"/>Countrey to ſecure <hi>New Caſtle</hi> for the intereſt of the Army, which he did effectually and honorably like a Soldier; and whilſt he ſtaid there, governed it in Juſtice, honeſty and peace; but was in ſhort time privatly undermi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and worm-eaten out of his governmentſhip by Sir <hi>Arthur Haſelrig,</hi> who as may be eaſily demonſtrated, had itching fingers after ſome poor <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habs</hi> Vineyard or other, and it may be in his own thoughts could neither by Law nor equity come by it, unleſs he could attain to be governour of that Town, and in pomp and glory with his Soldiers round about him, ſit as Judge and party in his own caſe, to over awe thereby if it were poſſible, both Jury and Judge; that ſo by intereſt and power he might get that, which before neither by Law nor equity he could obtain; all or the moſt part of which, was to the purpoſe ſhortly manifeſted in poor Mr. <hi>Collinwoods</hi> caſe divers hundred pounds <hi>per-annum</hi> thick, and then to diſinable him and his poſterity for ever, to lift up their heads againſt Sir <hi>Arthur.</hi> when times as to him ſhall mend, to recover their Inheritance again, he got him put in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Act for ſale of Delinquents eſtates, for all the reſt behind; but as to me it ſeems, being by my ſelf and Mr. <hi>John Muſgrave</hi>'s pens purſued for his injuſtice, he thought it pollicy to be the means of getting him out again, leaſt it might be made uſe of by either of us to his ſuine, but yet in the words of the Order there is ſuch a clauſe as may be a ſufficient rod over the <hi>Collinwoods</hi> back to keep him in awe, for ſo much as talking of Sir <hi>Arthurs</hi> unjuſt proceedings with him; I ſay in order to this and the like my bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther unawares, was by Sir <hi>Arthur</hi> undermined, and thruſt out of his go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment without (as he hath often told me) as ever having ſo much as a complement from Sir <hi>Arthur</hi> for it; and my brother like a ſoft and quiet ſpirited man gives way unto it, without ſo much as one Ruffle.</p>
            <p>And my Father and Uncle having had former acquaintance with Sir <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thur,</hi> and judged him ſo Godly, juſt and honeſt, as the like could ſcarce be found in England, and my Uncle having high obligations upon him to Sir <hi>Arthur</hi> for being ſo zealous for him in 1641. in delivering his Petition to the then Houſe of Commons for reparations for his foreſaid ſufferings, they did not regard the aforeſaid affront done to my eldeſt brother, but bleſs themſelves in the happineſs they were like to enjoy, by having ſo good a man as they then reputed Sir <hi>Arthur</hi> to be, to be their Governor; and ſo made it their work to be ſerviceable (with all reſpect) to him and the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick intereſt, which they conceived to be concerned in him, and having an extraordinary fair viſible Correſpondency with him, they took the opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity ſome years ago, to write a Letter to him for a zealous Parliamentiet (which is ſomething rate in that county) and to intreat him to fix his eie up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him for ſuch a place, but upon the reading the Letter, it ſeems Sir <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thur</hi> ſweld, and told him to this effect, that if he expected good from him, he muſt not be ſo fixed to the two <hi>Lilburns,</hi> for ſaith he, they are ſtiff obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate men, and oppoſed old Sir <hi>Henry Vane,</hi> and Sir <hi>William Armin,</hi> and in time will oppoſe me: But the man being underſtanding, kept this many months in his own breaſt, from my Father and Uncle, till now of late by accident it was told to the one of them; but they not knowing the ranker of Sir <hi>Arthurs</hi> heart againſt them, went on in their old honeſt blunt way
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:165914:3"/>(for ſo I ſhall call it till I ſee ſomething fairly proved againſt them) in do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their duty without favour or affection, and being ſomething rigid, and not enſie to be byaſed in their imployment, Sir <hi>Arthur</hi> had a minde to have my Uncle <hi>George</hi> as he was a Surveyer of Biſhops lands, to make him ſome repriſals for his great Lordſhip of Biſhop <hi>Auckland,</hi> which in conſcience he could not ſay Amen unto; upon which grew he firſt clear demonſtration of a viſible grudge betwixt them: and the ſecond was occaſioned by Sir <hi>Arthurs</hi> Steward one Mr. <hi>Colſon,</hi> who was alſo a Surveyer of the ſame lands, who counterfeting my Uncles hand, upon which my Uncle complained againſt him as a forgerer; whereupon the ſaid <hi>Colſon</hi> arreſted him in an acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſome thouſands of pounds, and caſt him into the <hi>Counter</hi> priſon at <hi>London,</hi> ſuppoſing he could not have got bail for ſuch a ſum; in which he was miſtaken but never durſt to this day declare againſt my Uncle, leſt in the concluſion it ſhould have coſt the ſaid <hi>Colſon</hi> his ears for his ſaid For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gery. The third viſible occaſion was about the coming in of <hi>Hamilton,</hi> Sir. <hi>Arthur</hi> endeavoured to get my Uncle to joyn with him in laying on 4 <hi>s.</hi> per Chaldron Exciſe upon coals, and for that purpoſe ſent for him from <hi>Sunder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> a coal town, where my Uncle had a little power, as well as Sir <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thur</hi> had at <hi>New-Caſtle</hi> a great one, and preſt him to do the one at one place, as he did intend to do the other at the other place; but my Uncle be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a warie underſtanding old man, he could not nor would not do it, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Sir <hi>Arthur</hi> could ſhew him the Parliaments commands for ſo doing, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that if he did it without Authority, it might be the ruin of him and all his; but Sir <hi>Arthur</hi> replied to this effect, The Parliament was a baſe wicked Parliament, and he would do it though he died for it; and when he went about to lay it on, the ſeamen demanding the ſight of his Commiſſion, he clapt his hand upon the hilt of his ſword, and told them that was his Commiſſion, and with that he would juſtifie it. Thus much for my for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorns: Now to the main and cloſe joyning of the battel of Sir <hi>Arthurs</hi> clear and viſible diſcovery of himſelf againſt my Uncle.</p>
            <p>The fourth viſible heart-burning within my cogniſance ariſes from this oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion, that Mr. <hi>John Blackſton</hi> late a Parliament man, being a Prebends ſon, and being allied to divers of the great Malignants in our Countrey, as Dr. <hi>Coſens</hi> his brother in Law, and ſeveral others like him: he very much en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours to protect them from Sequeſtration; and he finding my Father and Uncle (who were both Committee men made by Ordinance of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment dated <hi>April</hi> 1643. as well as himſelf) to be ſomewhat ſtiff, and that they would not ſell their ſouls and conſciences for greatneſs ſake and relations ſake; therefore did Mr. <hi>Thomas Shadforth,</hi> the ſaid Mr. <hi>Blackſtons</hi> brother in Law, pick a hole in my Uncles coat, for ſigning two Warrant at <hi>New Caſtle</hi> in 1642. when he was under force and power, on purpoſe to ſave himſelf from Sequeſtration, he being then charged, and it proved againſt him for a Cavalier in the firſt Warr, all which my Uncle in his printed Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrance to the Parliament, dated <hi>March</hi> 18. 1649, hath ſet forth; and Mr. <hi>John Blackſton</hi> all that while ſufficiently and groundleſly reproaching my Uncle in the then Houſe of Commons for a notorious Delinquent Cava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lier; and thereby gradually got him turned out of thoſe places of truſt
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:165914:3"/>the Parliament had repoſed in him, that thereby he might the eaſilyer tram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple upon him: and was not onely content to pay my Uncle, but alſo fell up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on me, as I have punctually declared in my Epiſtle o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the ſeave<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> of <hi>April</hi> 1651. Writ to Maſter <hi>John Price,</hi> Sir <hi>Arthurs</hi> P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n-A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent; which he durſt never anſwer to this day; to which Epiſtle for this particular, I refer you and the inquiſitive Reader, where you and he ſhall finde ſufficient foul play offered by Sir <hi>Arthur.</hi> But this buſineſs at the laſt coming to a Committee of Parliament, Sir <hi>Arthur</hi> it may bee finding it was advantageous to him to joyn with the ſaid Mr <hi>Blakiſton</hi> to cruſh my Vncle, that ſo he might be rid of him and his oppoſition, and thereby to the boot ove aw (if it were poſſible) my Eather, to a ſlaviſh and beaſtly complyance with him, he did more then ordinary (being Chairman to the ſaid Committee) appear againſt my ſaid Vncle; but I did to his face ſufficiently tell him of his unworthy doings in the Country in the ſaid caſe: but being my ſelf committed to the Tower about that time, viz. upon the 28. of <hi>March,</hi> 1649. although then Sir <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thur</hi> could not fully have his will of my ſaid Vncle at that time, for the Committee voted him a clear and honeſt man, and ordered to Report him ſo to the Houſe; yet I being ſo in priſon, Sir <hi>Arthur</hi> then thought to the purpoſe to cruſh to pieces, and root up by the roots our whole Family, and in order to that fell upon my bones to the purpoſe, to ſeek my total diſtruction, which is particularly touched in that Book proved at my Tryall to be mine, ſaving the Printers Errata's which were many, called <hi>A preparative to an Hue and Cry after Sir</hi> Arthur Haſelrig. <hi>pag,</hi> 4, 5 7, 8. and particularly in the caſe of my money, which was mine by di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Votes, Orders, and Ordinances of Parliament; yet although the <hi>Councel</hi> of <hi>State</hi> impriſoned me for Treaſon, and the Parliament approved thereof, yet they were ſo juſt and righteous, as not to or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der my eſtate to be ſeiſed upon, till I was convicted of ſome crime; yet Sir <hi>Arthur Haſelrig</hi> did aſſume that power to himſelf, as without authority, either from Parliament or Councel of State, to ſeaſe upon, or ſtop and deſtroy the current of my Ordinance of Parliament, ſo that I could not get a penny of almoſt 2500 <hi>l.</hi> in the day of my adverſity, to buy me, my wife and three little babes a bit of bread; of which doings of his being certified by my Father, I confeſs it did not drive me into a little rage and paſſion, and put thoſe provocations upon me, that had like to have been my ruin and deſtruction, and I think Sir <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thur</hi> expoſed me to as ſad a condition as any man in the world could be expoſed to, by his being inſtrumentall to get me into priſon for Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and then cloſe impriſoned, and my Friends and relations kept from me, and no allowance then from any: And beſides all this, to keep all my own Eſtate from me, and call me Traytor and Villain to my Father, when he demanded ſome of my Mony for the ſupportation of me, my wife and children, then in the greateſt diſtreſs that it was poſſible for any people in the world to be in: O the height of cruelty and bloodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:165914:4"/>in this Sir <hi>Arthur!</hi> Nay, to add to this, that thus to provoke and neceſſitate me, and then at <hi>Durham</hi> to threaten and tell my Father, Hee would come up to <hi>London</hi> to get me hanged for crying out of that which really and truly aroſe from his unſufferable oppreſſing of me; yea, and I have from good hands been told, ſuch an influence Sir <hi>Arthur</hi> had up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on my tryall for my Life, That after the Scaffolds were begun to bee built in Guildhall, my Tryall was delayed a week for his comming to Town, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o lay his modell for my ruine. And after that by the ſpecial providence of God I was freed from his bloodthirſtineſſe, he kept my Money in his, and his Treaſurers hands ſo long, without letting me have a penny of it to ſupport me, being then at liberty, and thereby expoſed to the utmoſt extremity in a manner that could bee, that I was in my own ſpirit compelled to tell his Clerk, Mr <hi>Pearſon,</hi> at the George in <hi>Chanell-Row,</hi> That his Maſter (Sir <hi>Arthur</hi>) had expoſed me, by keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing my Mony from me, to the utmoſt extremity, and have it from him I muſt and would, although it coſt me my heart blood; and ſo I deſired him before witneſs to tell him; And that if he thought to keep it while I ſued him at Law, or complained to the Houſe of him, it was a vain thing for him to think ſo, for he was too great for me that way to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter with, and I too much under a cloud in ſuch a way to expect any remedy from him; and beſides, I neither had Money nor time to ſpend upon him; and therefore as he loved his Maſters life and welfare, I intreated him to tell him, I wore a good Dagger by my right ſide, and a good Rapier by my left ſide, and if within 8 days he did not ſend me all my Money, or give me ſome rationall ſatisfaction, let him look to himſelf, for after that day, wherever I met him, I would pay him for all together, though I were cut in a thouſand pieces on the very place: For if againſt a thief that ſets upon me upon the Highway to rob me of a little Mony, it was lawfull for me to draw my ſword, and in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of my propriety to kill him; much more was it lawfull for me to doe the like to him that would (moſt arbitrarily and tyrannically with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all ſhadow or colour of Law) take al that ever I had, and therby ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe me, my wife and children to famiſh and periſh: And in caſe by my fair dealing with him, by telling him before hand of my intention, he got me committed to priſon, and thereby thought to diſenable mee to deal with him, he would be very much miſtaken, for thereby the hand would only be changed: Whereupon, within the time limited, (to the beſt of my remembrance) I had, &amp; received a Paper or Warrant, ſigned by Sir <hi>Arthur</hi> and Colonel <hi>George Fenwick</hi> to the Treaſurer at <hi>Newcaſtle,</hi> to pay me or my Aſſignes about 800 <hi>l.</hi> which I accordingly received: And at the Lord Generall <hi>Cromwels</hi> coming out of <hi>Ireland,</hi> he was Nobly pleaſed to get me a grant of ſelling Lands upon Me for the reſidue of my Money; for which moſt noble favour I muſt and doe heartily declare and acknowledg my ſelf highly obliged to him.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:165914:4"/>But I muſt acquaint you that when Sir <hi>Arthur</hi> had got me to priſon, and robbed me of my eſtate, for no better I can call it, although he ſhould tell me my father was one of the Committee, where it was diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of; yet I muſt tell him, his will was, and is a Law to all the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittees in the North, and ſo abſolute he is amongſt them, that ſome of them have told me, he will neither ſuffer them to vote, nor ſtare a que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, but reſolve all himſelf, and bid the Clark enter it, for ſo it muſt be; I ſay, when he had got me faſt, (as is before declared) he then thought all was his own, and finding my Uncle the heavieſt man left, he falls point blank upon him, about the Colliery at <hi>Harraton,</hi> and thinks to do two works at once. <hi>viz.</hi> 1. Sufficiently to diſgrace and impoveriſh my Uncle thereby. And then 2. To inveſt <hi>Wray</hi> a Popiſh Delinquent in the title of it, that ſo from him he might either purchaſe it for a ſong; or if that could not be, get him put into the Act for ſale, as he hath done ſome others, and ſo get his own ſurveyers put in to ſurvey it, and by his agents either drown the Colliery, that it might be eſteemed but little worth at the ſurveying it, or elſe over awe them to make what re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prizals he pleaſed, (as in the like he hath partly done already) that ſo it might be his for a toy; for I beleeve ſcarce all the Lands and Collie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries in the County of <hi>Durham</hi> will ſatisfie his greedy appetite; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in order to the accompliſhment of both his foreſaid ends, he doth with force and violence, in the moſt tyranicalleſt way, that ever was done in <hi>England,</hi> ſequeſter the ſaid Colliery, in or about <hi>Sept.</hi> 1649.</p>
            <p>And in proceſs of time, Mr. <hi>Primate</hi> Landlord to my uncle, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peals to the Commiſſioners at Haberdaſhers-hall, in theſe words.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="petition">
                        <head>To the Honourable Commiſſioners, for compounding, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <head type="sub">The humble Petition of <hi>Joſiah Primate</hi> Citizen, and Letherſeller of <hi>London.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                           <salute>Sheweth,</salute>
                        </opener>
                        <p>THAT Your Petitioner being poſſeſſed lawfully of three parts in four to be divided of all the Cole Mines in <hi>Harraton</hi> in the County of <hi>Durham,</hi> for divers yeers yet to come, by vertue of a Leaſe thereof made by Sir <hi>John Hed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worth</hi> Knight, in <hi>Decemb. 4. Caroli,</hi> upon good conſideration for <hi>41.</hi> years, and by mean aſſignments now come unto your Petitioner: And notwithſtanding that your Petitioner, and thoſe under whom he claimes, hath ſtill ſithence quietly wrought in the ſaid Cole Mines, and enjoyed three parts thereof, till <hi>Aug. 1649.</hi> And though the ſame three parts are notoriouſly known to be your Petitioners, yet hath the Committee of <hi>Durham</hi> ſequeſtred all the ſaid Cole Mines, as ſuppoſing the ſame to belong unto one <hi>Thomas Wray</hi> Eſquire a Delinquent, who in truth was never poſſeſſed nor enjoyed more then the fourth part, which your Petitioner claimes not.</p>
                        <p>And therefore your Petitioner humbly prays, That he may be admitted to make good his title to the ſaid three parts; which being ſo done that he may be reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to the Poſſeſſion, and benefit thereof: And that in the mean while upon ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity given to anſwer the profits to the ſtate, in caſe your Petitioner hath
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:165914:5"/>no right in regard by the oath annexed, it appears, he, and thoſe under whom he claims have been in Poſſeſſion theſe <hi>11.</hi> years and above, he may be admitted to work in the ſaid Cole Mines.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>
                              <hi>And he ſhall pray,</hi> &amp;c. Joſiah Primate.</signed>
                           <signed>
                              <hi>Copia vera exam.</hi> John Leech.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>Upon the Reading of which Petition, the Commiſſioners made an Order, the copy of which thus followeth:</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="order">
                        <head>By the Commiſſioners for compounding, &amp;c.</head>
                        <opener>
                           <dateline>
                              <date>
                                 <hi>12. Junii, 1650.</hi>
                              </date>
                           </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>Pon the Petition of <hi>Joſiah Primat,</hi> Citizen and Leatherſeller of London, (hereunto annexed) it is Ordered, That it be referred to Mr <hi>Reading</hi> to pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſe the ſaid Petition, and to report the ſtate of the caſe to us.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>Copia vera, Exam. <hi>Jo. Leech.</hi>
                           </signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>A copy of which Order, being (it ſeems) ſent to <hi>Durham,</hi> an anſwer is returned unto it, the copy of which thus followeth:</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Gentlemen,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>IN anſwer to your Order dated <hi>12.</hi> Iunii, <hi>1650.</hi> granted upon the Petition of Mr <hi>Joſiah Primat,</hi> we have here incloſed ſent you the true ſtate of that Caſe, concerning <hi>Harraton</hi> Colliery, and the States intereſt in it; which we conceive is very clear: VVe are <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                        <desc> _____ </desc>
                     </gap> Gent'</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Your affectionate friends and ſervants,</hi> Arthur Haſelrige. Francis Wren. Tho. Delavall.</signed>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Copia Vera exam.</hi> John Leech.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Which encloſed certificare, or ſtate of <hi>Harraton</hi> Colliery, being one of the notorious falſe ones, that I think can be made, and contains in it the ſum of the ranker of Sir <hi>Arthur</hi>'s heart, and the ultimate of what can be ſaid by him againſt my Uncle; I ſhall here inſert the copy of it, which thus followeth;</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="certificate">
                        <opener>
                           <dateline>
                              <hi>Dunelm.</hi>
                           </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>UPon the ſixth day of Auguſt 1649. <hi>Thomas Wray</hi> of <hi>Beaniſh</hi> in this County of <hi>Durham</hi> Eſquire, made complaint to the Committee of Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtrations for this County, that Mr. <hi>George Lilburn</hi> and Mr. <hi>George Grey,</hi> two of the ſaid Committee, had entred into and poſſeſſed themſelves of his Colieries, and ſeverall houſes thereunto belonging in <hi>Harraton,</hi> and that his eſtate and coliery in <hi>Harraton</hi> was ſequeſtred for his being a Recu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant, and for his being in <hi>Newcaſtle</hi> when it was the enemies Garriſon; and that the ſaid Mr. <hi>Lilburn</hi> and Mr. <hi>Grey</hi> had raiſed great ſummes of money out of the ſame, and converted it to their own proper uſes, which ought to have been paid unto the State; and that they ſtill hold poſſeſſion thereof, to
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:165914:5"/>the great loſſe and prejudice of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth. And upon examination of Witneſſes upon<note n="a">But I am ſure their Depoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions are no where to be found; Sir <hi>Arthur</hi> it ſeems not daring to truſt Mr. <hi>Gilpm</hi> the Clerk to take them, but onely his owne Secretary, who was no Record-keeper of that Committee And what they were, or where they are, is not to be found.</note> Oath before the Committee i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that in the yeare 1644. Sir <hi>William Armyn</hi> and the reſt of the Commiſſioners of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ſequeſtred the coliary of <hi>Harraton</hi> then in the ſole poſſeſſion of the ſaid Mr. <hi>Wrey,</hi> and ſold one thouſand pounds worth of coals that was upon the Staythes And further, that the Committee of Sequeſtrations for this county granted an Order in the year 1645. upon the petition of Mrs <hi>Wray</hi> wife to the ſaid <hi>Tho. Wray,</hi> (Mr. <hi>Geo. Lilburn</hi> and Mr. <hi>Geo. Greys</hi> hands being at the ſaid Order) for letting the ſaid coliery at <hi>Harraton</hi> to one <hi>Pearſon</hi> for the payment of the creditors of Mr. <hi>Wray.</hi> And the ſaid <hi>Pearſen</hi> was to give an account thereof to the Commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tee. <hi>Which Pearſon did enter into the Colery</hi>
                           <note n="b">This is the groſſeſt untruth that can be told: For <hi>Pearſon</hi> ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver took the ſaid Colery.</note> 
                           <hi>accordingly.</hi> But it doth not appear to us that the ſaid <hi>Pearſon</hi> was ever cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to give any account to the Committee. And it further appeared to us, that the ſaid coliery continued to bee wrought by Mr. <hi>Wray's</hi> Agents for his uſe, till June in the yeare 1647, And that about April in the yeare 1647. Mr. <hi>George Lilburne</hi> and Mr. <hi>George Grey</hi> ſent to the aforeſaid <hi>Thomas Wray</hi> to deſire a meeting with him to treat about buying out his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtare in the ſaid coliery. Accordingly they met at <hi>Ferryboat</hi> about Eaſter in the yeare 1647. Upon their meeting <hi>Thomas Wray</hi> told the ſaid Mr. <hi>Lilburne</hi> and Mr. <hi>Grey,</hi> that they very well knew that coliery to be of very great value, and that it was <hi>worth above</hi> 3000. <hi>l. per annum,</hi> and that he was out in monies for that colery at leaſt 16000. l. yet in reſpect of the condition he was now in, he was contented to ſell his whole eſtate in it for 5000. l. That he would have one thouſand pound paid down for his own uſe, and one thouſand more to ſtop the clamors of his creditors; and that he would take further time to conſider what dayes to require the payments of the other three thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand pounds upon. It was affirmed that Mr. <hi>George Lilburne</hi> did then ſay, That for the payment of the firſt 2000 l. they ſhould not differ; and that Mr. <hi>Wray</hi> having there his Evidences for that colery, they being viewed by Mr. <hi>George Lilburne</hi> and Mr. <hi>George Grey,</hi> Mr. <hi>Lilburne</hi> told the ſaid Mr. <hi>wray</hi> that he did not think that Mr. <hi>Wray</hi> could have produced ſo cleare a Title for 7 parts of 8 in that colery; but for the 8 part he was not ſo fully ſatisfied. Mr. <hi>Wray</hi> then told him, that there was one <hi>Comadale</hi> that pretended a Title to that 8 part; but he conceived that he had ſufficient to make it good, that that part was in him alſo. But told Mr. <hi>Lilburne</hi> that howſoever he knew <hi>Comadale</hi> would part with his intereſt upon very eaſie termes. There was then a new day appointed for another meeting for Mr. <hi>Wray's</hi> appointing the other dayes for the payment of the 3000. l. And Mr. <hi>Lilburn</hi> in his go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from that place, he met with one Mr. <hi>Swaine,</hi> and the ſaid Mr. <hi>Lilburne</hi> told him that he was agreed with Mr. <hi>Wray</hi> for the ſaid colery. A little be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:165914:6"/>the appointed day of meeting, great rains fell, and the Rivers roſe ſo high, that it hindered the meeting. Immediatly after the ſaid Mr. <hi>Lilburne</hi> and Mr. <hi>Grey</hi> went to <hi>London,</hi> and made ſome agreement with the ſaid Mr. <hi>Commondale</hi> about the 8 part as they pretend but nothing ſhown to make it good. And comming down in June following, they entred into and poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed themſelves of the whole colery aforeſaid, and it hath been wrought by them ever ſince to their own uſes and benefits.</p>
                        <p>And for that it plainly appeared unto the Committee that the Colery<note n="c">This is as falſe as can be: For the nine and five quarter Seams of Coles were not in work at all in <hi>1644, 1645,</hi> nor <hi>1646,</hi> nor never was ſequeſtred by any in the world till <hi>1649.</hi> that Sir <hi>Arthur</hi> by his Will and Sword ſequeſtred it.</note> was ſequeſtred by Sr. <hi>William Armine</hi> in the yeare 1644. and that it had been ſolely in the poſſeſſion of Mr. <hi>Wray</hi> and his Agents three years before that, and that it was let by the Committee of Sequeſtrations in the yeare 1645. And that no other had clai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med any intereſt in it untill Mr. <hi>George Lilburn</hi> and Mr. <hi>George Grey,</hi> two of the Committee poſſeſſed themſelves of it. And that there had been no Order made either by the Lords and Commons for Sequeſtrations, or the Committee of Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtrations in the County, nor that there had been any Authority for the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſting and diſpoſſeſſing of the State of their intereſt, and that Mr. <hi>Wray</hi> as being a Recuſant and Delinquent, was uncapable of compoſition, the Committee made this Order.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Decimo tertio die Auguſti.</hi> 1649.</p>
                        <p>Upon hearing of <hi>Thomas Wray, George Lilburne,</hi> and <hi>George Grey</hi> Eſquires, It appeared to this Committee, that in the year 1644. Sir <hi>William Armine</hi> did ſequeſter the Colliery at <hi>Harraton,</hi> belonging to Mr. <hi>Wray</hi> for the uſe of the State, and that the faid Colliery was then wrought for the uſe of the ſaid Mr. <hi>Wray</hi> and his aſſignes, and for no other, and that the ſame was ſince let by this Committee <hi>in the yeer</hi> 1645. <hi>for one whole year to one</hi> Pearſon: And that it doth not appear that the ſequeſtration was not at any time taken off: It is therefore thought fit, and ſo ordered by the ſaid Committee, that the ſequeſtration ſhall be continued upon the ſaid Colliery for the uſe of the State, and that all thoſe, who have had any uſe or profit of the ſaid Colliery, ſince the ſame was ſequeſtred, ſhall forthwith make their accounts, that it may appear what profits have been made thereof in that time, and immediately after the making this order, Mr. <hi>George Lilburne</hi> then ſitting at the Committee, and being one of the Committee, deſired that he might have time given him to make his title good, to the eſtate he claimed in that Colliery, the Committee bad him to appoint his time, he then <hi>deſired a full moneth,</hi> and it was gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: Thereupon he went to <hi>London,</hi> and by the aforeappointed day he brought down with him one Mr. <hi>Levit,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Joſiah Primatt;</hi> who with their Councel went to the Committee: The Councel being then put up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it, to ſhew what title either Mr. <hi>Levitt,</hi> Mr. <hi>Primatt,</hi> or Mr. <hi>Lilburne</hi> had, affirmed that Mr. <hi>Wray</hi> had gotten their Evidences, and would have had the Committee to have compelled him to have produced his title: The Committee then replied, that the matter was of very great
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:165914:6"/>concernment to the State, <hi>the Colliery being worth</hi> 3000. l. <hi>per Annum.</hi> and that Mr. <hi>Lilburne</hi> had made of it, after he had put the State out of poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion at leaſt 15. <hi>l. per diem,</hi> for about a year together, as they were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed by thoſe that knew it very well, and that they durſt not be ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>falſe to their truſt, as when the State had been in poſſeſſion above three years, to produce Evidences to diveſt the State: and what they deſired was ſuch a thing, as was never heard in any Court, That a Plaintiff that ſued for the poſſeſſion of Land, ſhould deſire the Defendant to make him a Title to out himſelf: And that if <hi>Wray</hi> had gotten their Eviden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces into his hand, their way was plain, to exhibite a Bill in Chancery, &amp; there they might compel him to produce his Evidences in a legal way: And it not appearing to the Committee, that either Mr. <hi>Lilburne,</hi> Mr. <hi>Levitt,</hi> or Mr. <hi>Joſiah Primatt,</hi> would, or then could produce the leaſt Evidence to overthrow Mr. <hi>Wrays</hi> title, Mr. <hi>Wray</hi> being then preſent and confidently affirming and holding his Evidence in his hand ready to make it good; that the right of the whol Colliery was in him, they confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med their former order, and have ſince let the ſaid Colliery for the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of the State: And we do now deſire that you would be pleaſed to call Mr. <hi>George Lilburne</hi> and Mr. <hi>George Grey</hi> to account for the profits of the ſaid Colliery; we being aſſured that great ſums of money are in their hands due to the Publick, they having as yet paid never a penny, <hi>And we hope this is a full anſwer to your Order procured by Mr.</hi> Joſiah Primatt, <hi>dated</hi> July <hi>the</hi> 12. 1650. <hi>concerning his</hi> intereſt in the Cole Mines at <hi>Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raton,</hi> and ſent down to us for our Certificate.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>
                              <list>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>Arthur Haſilrige.</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>Francis Wren.</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>Tho. Delaval.</hi>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </signed>
                           <date>
                              <hi>Auguſt</hi> 8 1650.</date>
                           <signed>Copia vera Exam. <hi>Jo. Leech.</hi>
                           </signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>Now I ſhall deſire you to take notice, that the chief title here ſet up, is <hi>Wray</hi>'s own bare averments, who is a Delinquent Papiſt, and one of the baſeſt of that ſect, being a common procurer of affidavit men; and a fellow that will ſwear any thing in the world, it being his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon habit, in his common diſcourſe, as you your ſelves very well know, for which you lately reproved him in open Court, though he was too much your friend to be puniſhed therfore by you: but in counter-ballance to his lying averments before mentioned, I could produce you he oaths of my Uncle and Mr. <hi>Grey,</hi> two men of honor, conſcience, and repute; but they being much both at one, and my Uncle a party, and Mr. <hi>Grey</hi> none, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though you lately made him one, againſt all reaſon and juſtice. I ſhall onely inſert Mr. <hi>Greys;</hi> The Copy of whoſe oath thus followeth.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="oath">
                        <p>
                           <hi>GEorge Gray</hi> of <hi>Harraton</hi> in the County of <hi>Durham</hi> Gentleman, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth Oath that in the year 1644. Sir <hi>William Armin</hi> and other Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners of Parliament, did Sequeſter certain Colemynes, or ſeams of coals in <hi>Harraton</hi> in the ſaid County of <hi>Durham,</hi> then belonging to one <hi>John Jackſon</hi> Gentl. a Delinquent, and certain other Colemynes or ſeams of coals in <hi>Harraton</hi> aforeſaid, then belonging to <hi>Thomas Wray</hi> Eſquire a Papiſt
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:165914:7"/>and Delinquent; which ſeams of coals belonging to the ſaid Mr. <hi>Wray,</hi> were onely the half yard and 3 quarter ſeam of coals, the greater ſeams of coal, <hi>viz.</hi> the five quarter ſeam and nine quarter ſeam being then drowned and not won or wrought. And he further depoſeth that on or about the 6 of <hi>Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bruary</hi> 1645. upon the ſaid Mr. <hi>Wrays</hi> Petition on the behalf of his creditors, the Committee for Sequeſtrations for the ſaid County, Ordered that Mr. <hi>Rich. Pearſon</hi> of <hi>New Coſtle,</hi> or any other of Mr. <hi>Wrays</hi> creditors well affected, that would undertake the working of the ſaid colemines, called the half yard and three quarter coal, ſhould have a leaſe thereof granted for one year, there being then no coals of the ſaid Mr. <hi>VVrays</hi> viſible but onely the coals that did come from the two ſeams commonly called the half yard and three quarter ſeams, the five quarter ſeams and nine quarter ſeams being then ungained, the profits whereof ſhould be all wed to the ſaid creditors, but neither the ſaid <hi>Pearſon</hi> nor any other of the ſaid Mr. <hi>Wrays</hi> creditors did accept of any leaſe to work the ſaid mynes: And this Deponent knoweth that neither the ſaid Mr. <hi>VVray,</hi> nor any of his Agents, did from thenceforth to this day, work any part of the ſaid coalmynes, except the workmen of the grounds got ſome for their own fire; And he alſo knoweth that Capt. <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Lilburn</hi> took an eſtate of the eight part of the ſaid five quarter coal and nine quarter coal, from <hi>VVilliam Commondale</hi> Gentleman for certain years not yet expired; and the ſaid Mr <hi>Wray</hi> pretending to have ſome eſtate in another ſhare of the ſaid ſeams, called the five quarter and nine quarter coal; He, this Deponent, and Mr <hi>George Lilburn</hi> at the deſire of the ſaid Mr. <hi>VVray</hi> by his Servant <hi>William Madiſon,</hi> did give Mr. <hi>VVray</hi> a meeting at <hi>Ferry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boat</hi> in the ſaid county about <hi>April</hi> or <hi>May</hi> (as he remembreth the time, to ſee what eſtate the ſaid Mr. <hi>VVray</hi> could make to the ſaid ſeams of five quarter and nine quarter coal, where the ſaid Mr. <hi>VVray</hi> did ſhew deeds that intitled him to a fourth part, and no more of the ſaid ſeams of nine and five quarter coal, for the tearm of certain years, then and yet unexpired; but nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther this Deponent nor the ſaid <hi>George Lilburn</hi> (to this Deponents know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge) ever offered the ſaid Mr. <hi>VVray</hi> 5000 <hi>l</hi> or any other ſum at all for his intereſt in the ſaid coalmine, but told him if he could inable himſelf to work his ſhare, they would be content to joyn with him in the winning and recovering the ſaid Mynes, and ſo referred the buſineſs to another mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, but they never after gave him any further meeting about it, well know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him to be a Delinquent, and all his his eſtate to be liable to Sequeſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. And he further depoſeth that he never heard, nor doth he in the leaſt believe, that <hi>Mr. George Lilburn</hi> did acknowledge to the ſaid <hi>Mr. VVray,</hi> that he the ſaid <hi>Mr. Wray</hi> had a title to 7 parts of 8 of the ſaid Colliery, and the rather believes it, foraſmuch as the ſaid Mr. <hi>Lilburn</hi> at the ſaid meeting au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dibly read over the Deeds of the ſaid Mr. <hi>Wray,</hi> by the which there did no more in the leaſt to the beſt of this Deponents underſtanding, appeare due to him but barely a fourth part. And the ſaid M <hi>George Lilburn</hi> ſaid then unto the ſaid Mr. <hi>Wray,</hi> that he could not have believed, that the ſaid Mr. <hi>Wray</hi> had had ſo cleare a Title to his fourth part, had he not ſo plainly read it in the ſaid Deeds. And he further believes, that the ſaid Mr. <hi>George Lilburne</hi> did not then nor any time ſince, acknowledge that the ſaid Mr. <hi>Wray</hi> had a good
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:165914:7"/>right to 7 parts of 8 of the ſaid colery, foraſmuch as he hath often heard the ſaid Mr <hi>George Lilburne</hi> affirm, that in or about the year 1641. hee was cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen a Commiſſioner by Mr <hi>Morley</hi> in a Suit in Chancery depending, for examining witneſſes betwixt the ſaid M. <hi>Morley</hi> and one Mr. <hi>Lewis</hi> and Mr. <hi>Levet;</hi> which commiſſion was ſet upon at <hi>Northalerton</hi> in the county of <hi>York,</hi> where the ſaid <hi>Thomas Wray</hi> was examined as a principall witneſſe for the clearing of the eſtate of the colery, the thing in controverſie, and he the ſaid <hi>Wray,</hi> did then and there poſitively ſwear, that his right was no more but a fourth part of the ſaid colliery in queſtion, as by the ſaid depoſitions upon Record in the Court of Chancery, reference being thereunto had, more fully appeareth, unto which this Deponent referreth himſelf; neither doth he believe that the ſaid <hi>George Lilburn</hi> did ever tell one Mr. <hi>Swayne</hi> mentioned in Sir <hi>Arthur Haſlerigs</hi> Certificate, that he the ſaid <hi>Lilburn</hi> had made an agreement with the ſaid <hi>VVray</hi> for any part of the ſaid colliery, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can he believe or can imagin it poſſible, that ever the ſaid <hi>Wray</hi> hath diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burſed 16000 <hi>l.</hi> about or in the managing of the ſaid colliery, for as much as he could never hear him in the leaſt at any time to be judged a man in lands, ſtock or credit, able to lay out ſuch an eſtate as 16000 <hi>l.</hi> is, although this deponent have known the ſaid Mr. <hi>VVray</hi> above 30. years. And this deponent further maketh Oath, That he hath known the ſaid colliery very nigh 40. years, and hath known many that have disburſed great ſums for the winnining thereof, who have all complained they have had great loſs, but never heard of any that gained any thing by i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>. And he further depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth, That after the meeting with the ſaid Mr. <hi>VVray,</hi> and peruſal of his deeds, and that it was informed that <hi>Jeſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>h Primat</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> Leather-ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, had the greateſt intereſt and ſhare of the ſaid colliery of the five quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and nine quarter coal, Mr. <hi>Lilburn</hi> and this deponent dealt with the ſaid Mr. <hi>Primat</hi> for a leaſe of the ſaid 5 quarter and 9 quarters ſeams, which was granted to the ſaid <hi>George Lilburn,</hi> and this deponents ſon <hi>George Gray</hi> the younger, for five years of the moity of the ſaid Mynes, and after thoſe five years ended, then for a further Leaſe for ſeaven years, of three quarters of the ſaid Mynes, under certain rents agreed on, by vertue of which leaſe, they entred and won and wrought the ſaid colliery: and in or about the Month of <hi>May</hi> 1648. by ill accident, the ſaid colliery was fired, and about 50 workmen thereby periſhed, and about <hi>Auguſt</hi> next after, the ſaid Mynes by a great ſtood were drowned, whereby he believeth the ſaid <hi>George Lil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burn</hi> and his ſon ſuffered great loſs, beſides one thouſand pounds and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards clear out of purſe; and afterwards the ſaid <hi>George Lilburn</hi> and his ſaid ſon, at their great charge, recovered the ſaid Mynes, and had and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed them til 1649 when the ſaid <hi>Thomas Wray</hi> enformed Sir <hi>Arthur Haſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rig</hi> and the Committee at <hi>Durham,</hi> that he had the intereſt of 7 parts of 8 to be divided of the ſaid colemynes; which the ſaid <hi>George Lilburn,</hi> being then one of the Committee, denied, and alledged that Mr. <hi>Wray</hi> had but onely a fourth part thereof, and that the other three parts belonged to the ſaid <hi>Joſich Primat</hi> and others; whereupon the Committee 13 <hi>Auguſt</hi> 1649 order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that all parties ſhould upon the 11 of <hi>September</hi> next following produce their writings and evidences touching their ſeveral titles and claims to the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:165914:8"/>ſaid colemynes, at which day the ſaid Mr. <hi>Primat</hi> and <hi>Thomas Levet</hi> Eſquire, under whom the ſaid Mr. <hi>Primat</hi> claims his intereſt, were come down from <hi>London</hi> to <hi>Durham,</hi> and was ready before the Committee to prove his ſaid ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, and brought with him his Councel, one Mr. <hi>Turner</hi> to plead his cauſe, who if he had been ſuffered, would have made as he believeth, the title clear; but was ſo taken up and affronted by Sir <hi>Arthur Haſelrig,</hi> who took upon him the whole matter, that Mr. <hi>Turner</hi> could not open the buſineſs, inſomuch that the ſtanders by did admire at ſuch injuſtice; yet Mr. <hi>Turner</hi> deſired that Mr <hi>Wray</hi> might produce certain deeds or leaſes of the ſaid Mynes which he had in his keeping; which concerned Mr <hi>Primat</hi> as well as Mr <hi>Wray;</hi> But Sir <hi>Arthur</hi> ſaid he ſhould not, then Mr. <hi>Turner</hi> deſired that Mr. <hi>Wray</hi> might declare the truth, which the ſaid Mr <hi>Wray</hi> ſaid he would; but Sir <hi>Arthur</hi> riſing up in an angry manner, ſhaked his hand towards the ſaid Mr. <hi>Wray,</hi> uttering theſe words, I charge you ſpeak not a word, for if you do, it ſhall be no better for them, and it ſhall be the worſe for you, for I know how to handle you; or words to that effect. And this Deponent further ſaith, that afterwards Sir <hi>A thur</hi> with Col. <hi>Fenwick</hi> and Col. <hi>Wren,</hi> drew up an Order privately, and brought it to the Clark of the Committee of <hi>Durham</hi> to enter it, contrary to the opinion and knowledge of ſome of the Committee, as by their Certificate under their hands, which this depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent hath lately ſeen, may appear.</p>
                        <p>And this Deponent further maketh oath that <hi>Mr. George Lilburne,</hi> and this Deponent was ſerved with a warrant to appear before the Lords and Commons, to anſwer a Petition preferred by Captain <hi>Francis Swayne</hi> one of <hi>Mr. Wray</hi>'s creditors, about <hi>January</hi> or <hi>February</hi> 1647. To the right honourable the Committee of Lords and Commons for ſequeſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; in which Petition he complained, that the ſaid <hi>Thomas Wray</hi> had a right to the ſaid Colliery of <hi>Harraton,</hi> which he valued at 16000. <hi>l.</hi> and was kept out of it by <hi>Mr. George Lilburne,</hi> and this Deponent, ſo that neither he nor the State for his Delinquency could injoy any benefit by it; Upon which Petition the now L. chief Baron <hi>Wilde</hi> having then the Chaire there, paſſed an order to refer the conſideration of the Petition to <hi>Mr. John Bradſhaw</hi> now Lord Preſident; After which a ſet day of hearing was appointed, where divers members of Parliament appeared, and ſat upon the hearing of the buſineſs: And the now Lord Preſident as Councel for the State, was fully heard, and the ſaid <hi>Mr. Lilburne,</hi> and this Deponent having no Councel then preſent appeared, and the ſaid <hi>Mr. Lilburne</hi> gave the ſaid Lords and Commons, ſuch full ſatisfaction by demonſtrating his, and this Deponents ſons legal right to thoſe parts they now claim, and that the ſaid <hi>Mr. Wray</hi> had no right at all to any more then a fourth part, for which the ſaid <hi>Mr. Lilburne</hi> then offered the ſaid Lords and Commons; That if either their honors, or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for the uſe of the State, or any other in the right of the ſaid Mr. <hi>Wray,</hi> would put in their Stock, he the ſaid <hi>George Lilburne,</hi> and his Partners would be true Accomptants, and be very glad to yeild up to the ſaid <hi>Mr. Wray,</hi> or the State, or any other in his right a clear fourth part of profit, or any other larger proportion that could legally be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to belong to the ſaid <hi>Mr. Wray:</hi> upon which hearing, and proſers of
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:165914:8"/>the ſaid <hi>Mr. Lilburne,</hi> the ſaid Lords and Commons threw out the Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Complaint of the ſaid Captain <hi>Swayne,</hi> and openly at the board much commended the ſaid <hi>Mr. Lilburne,</hi> for his honeſt, fair, and juſt dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, and profers. And this Deponent further maketh oath, that he heard the ſaid <hi>Mr. Primatt</hi> ſay to Sir <hi>Arthur Haſelrige</hi> at <hi>Newcaſtle,</hi> it was in vain for us to come here, for he, the ſaid <hi>Mr. Primatt</hi> was told, that <hi>Mr. Wray</hi> told his friends, that ſir <hi>Arthur</hi> was to have the Colliery, and that he the ſaid ſir <hi>Arthur</hi> had undertaken to pay <hi>Mr. Wray</hi>'s debts, or words to that effect.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>George Grey.</signed>
                           <dateline>Jur. coram Comiſs. <date>
                                 <hi>Janurary</hi> 3. 1650.</date>
                           </dateline>
                           <signed>Will. Molins.</signed>
                           <signed>Copia vera Exam. <hi>Jo. Leech.</hi>
                           </signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>UPon which foreſaid Order of yours, or ſome of you, and others of the Commiſſioners, Mr. <hi>Reading</hi> perfected his report, the firſt of Februa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry 1650. &amp; the later end of that month, viz. the 27. day, we came to a hearing upon it, where Sir <hi>A thu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> appeared as the Proſecuter, and ſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haved himſelfe with ſweating, foaming, and dominiering, as, if he had had a priviledge to ingroſſe all the diſcourſe where ever he comes, and none elſe had a power to contradict what he ſaith: But you (as I will ſay) unjuſtly o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver-ruling our chiefeſt Depoſitions, (although our caſe in my judgement both as to poſſeſſion and Title, was made as clear as the Sunne by Mr. <hi>Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings</hi> Report) for which I have been ſeverall times told he was ſufficiently chid, for that he durſt be ſo honeſt:) upon which your over-ruling our ſaid Depoſitions, we let that petition fall, having liberty of right as alſo by your Order, we preferred a new one; and upon your Order thereupon, I rode almoſt fourſcore miles a day towards the county of <hi>Durham</hi> to fetch up new witneſſes, in ſuch weather that the wind and haile-ſtones had like to have beat out both my eyes (one of which to this very day I could never ſince per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly recover) and there I found our claim to be ſo clearly able to be made forth, both to title &amp; an uninterrupted poſſeſſion and that the 5 and 9 quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Seams of coals were never in this world in <hi>Wrayes</hi> ſole poſſeſſion, nor ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſequeſtred in 1644 for his delinquency, both of which is moſt falſly ſuggeſted in the foreſaid certificate of Sir <hi>Arthur,</hi> and the pretended Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee of <hi>Durham,</hi> that I judged it a caſe ſo juſt and honeſt, as that I might have comfort in it to venture both my life and eſtate in the defence of it, which I have ſince done, and to the death ſhall by Gods aſſiſtance ſtill doe; and what injuſtice you have ſince offered us in that caſe, cannot better in my judgement briefly be ſet forth, then by the inſerting Mr. <hi>Primats</hi> Petition to the Parliament upon Tueſday being the 22 of this preſent July 1691. the copy of which as it was in print delivered at the Parliament doore, thus followeth,</p>
            <q>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:165914:9"/>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="petition">
                        <head>To the Supreme Authority of this Nation, the Parliament of the Common-wealth of England.</head>
                        <head type="sub">The humble Petition of <hi>Joſiah Primat</hi> Citizen and Leatherſeller of <hi>LONDON.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>Sheweth,</opener>
                        <p>THat Sir <hi>John Hedwarth</hi> Knight, was ſeiſed in Fee of the Mannor and Cole-mines of <hi>Harraton</hi> upon <hi>Sunderland</hi> river in the county of <hi>Dur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> under whoſe Title your Petitioner and one <hi>Thomas Wray</hi> Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire, <hi>Anthony Metcalf,</hi> and <hi>William Commondell</hi> Gent. and their Aſſigns, were and are intereſſed for a long term of yeares yet in being in the two greater Seams of coal there, called the 9 and 5 quarter Seams viz. your Petitioner in one moity of thoſe Seams, the ſaid <hi>Thomas Wray</hi> in one quarter thereof, the ſaid <hi>Metcalf</hi> in one halfe quarter thereof, and the ſaid <hi>Commondell</hi> in the other half quarter thereof.</p>
                        <p>That in 1642. the ſaid Seams were loſt and drowned, and lay ſo loſt till 1647. when your Petitioner demiſed his ſaid moity to <hi>George Lilburne</hi> and <hi>George Gray Junio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>,</hi> Eſquires, for 12 years at certain Rents, who by the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence of at leaſt 1500 l. regained the ſame, and quietly enjoyed &amp; wrought them till 1648. the ſaid <hi>Wray</hi> and <hi>Metcalf</hi> neglecting and refuſing to joyn with them in that charge and work.</p>
                        <p>That in 1648. by a ſad miſchance with the loſſe of almoſt 60 mens lives, the ſaid Seams were fired and loſt again; but before the end of that year at the vaſt charge of your Petitioners ſaid tenants, they were regained, and quietly enjoyed and wrought by them till <hi>September</hi> 1649 to the great ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of the State in abating the price of coals, and increaſing Trade in that River.</p>
                        <p>That in <hi>September</hi> 1649 Sir <hi>Arthur Haſelrig</hi> acting as one of the Commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tee for Sequeſtrations, with two others, viz. Col. <hi>Fenwick,</hi> and Col. <hi>Francis Wren</hi> in the ſaid county, unjuſtly cauſed your Petitioners ſaid tenants to be diſpoſſeſſed of the ſaid Seams of coals and their utenſils to be ſeiſed &amp; taken from them, under pretence that the ſaid Seams wholly belonged to the ſaid <hi>Wray</hi> being a Papiſt Delinquent, and had been ſequeſtred as his eſtate in 1644. whereas in truth they were not then in being, being abſolutely drowned.</p>
                        <p>That your Petitioner being then in that county, by his Councell humbly moved that Committee before they ſequeſtred his eſtate, that either the ſaid <hi>Wray</hi> (who was then alſo in Court) might ſhew forth his Title and Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, (your Petitioner and his Tenants being in quiet poſſeſſion) or that the ſaid Order for the ſequeſtration of the ſaid 9 and 5 quarter Seams in 1644. might be produced. But Mr. <hi>Wray</hi> could neither produce any Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, nor Sir <hi>Arthur</hi> any ſuch Order, And yet your Petitioners ſaid eſtate was preſently ſequeſtred, and his Tenants ejected and diſpoſſeſſed, although
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:165914:9"/>he doth confidently believe that neither Sir <hi>Arthur</hi> nor colonel <hi>Fenwick</hi> had any legall right to act there as Sequeſtrators, having not taken the Oath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed by Ordinance of Parliament of 27 May 1644. for all members whatſoever of <hi>Committees of Sequeſtration</hi> to take before they intermeddle at all with Sequeſtration; and two of the legal <hi>Committee of Sequeſtration</hi> there, viz. col. <hi>Milford,</hi> and <hi>Rich. Lilburne</hi> Eſquire, did enter their Proteſt in the <hi>Committee Book</hi> againſt the unjuſt actings of the ſaid Sir <hi>Arthur Haſelrig;</hi> to which illegall practices of Sir <hi>Arthur,</hi> the major part of the Commiſſioners at Haberdaſhers Hall refuſed to ſuffer your Petitioner to examine his wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes to.</p>
                        <p>That your Petitioner appealed (which was upon the 28 <hi>June,</hi> 1650.) to the Commiſſioners for compounding, and before them was ready to make his title appear by good evidence, and particularly by the ſaid <hi>Wrays</hi> own de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions in Chancery, taken about 9 years ago in a cauſe then there depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding about the ſaid colliery, where he poſitively ſwears he hath but a fourth part; but in <hi>February</hi> laſt, when this buſineſs came to hearing, the Major part of the Commiſſioners rejected <hi>Wrays</hi> ſaid depoſitions in Chancery, and would not ſuffer them to be read. The firſt time that ever depoſitions in Chancery were refuſed for good evidence (eſpecially againſt the party ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring them) in any Court of Equity in <hi>England,</hi> that ever your Petitioner could hear of.</p>
                        <p>That thereupon by the Order of the ſaid Commiſſioners, your Petitio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner preferred a new Petition, (which was upon the of <hi>February,</hi> 1650.) before them, ſetting forth his title to, and poſſeſſion of the ſaid moiety of the ſaid Seams, and ſent above 200 miles for 7 or 8 ſubſtantial witneſſes, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral of which have lived a long time upon the place, and were workers a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the ſaid Colliery, and examined them, and ſtaid them here many days after at his own charge, that they might be croſs examined for the State. And after obtained<note n="*">As appears by their order da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted</note> publication in the cauſe, by conſent of the States Solicitor, and a report of the ſtate of the caſe, and got a day of hearing appointed, and an Order that Mr. <hi>Wray</hi> ſhould be preſent, and produce his deeds and evidences at the hearing: but the ſaid <hi>Wray</hi> (though duely ſummoned) appeared not the firſt day, nor the ſecond, nor third appointed days<note n="a" place="bottom">Which ſeveral days of hearing by the Commſſioners orders, were to be on Thurſday next come <hi>14</hi> days after the <hi>21</hi> May <hi>1651.</hi> and in three weeks next after the <hi>22</hi> May <hi>1651.</hi> and upon <hi>5</hi> June <hi>1651.</hi> they order that Wray ſhall forthwith appear to the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, upon notice of that Order.</note> of hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, till your Petitioner got him commanded up by the Councel of State.<note n="b" place="bottom">whoſe Order or Warrant is dated the <hi>10.</hi> June <hi>1651.</hi>
                           </note>
                        </p>
                        <p>That when the ſaid <hi>Wray</hi> was come up and ſhould have brought his deeds into Court, and gone to a ſpeedy hearing, according to your Petitioners ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation, and ſeveral Orders of the Commiſſioners for that end, the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jor part of them ordered the ſaid <hi>Wray</hi> ſix weeks longer day to bring in his deeds, and to attend the hearing, and that in the mean time he might exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min new witneſſes; which is held, (as your Petitioner is informed) a moſt dangerous courſe in all other Courts of Juſtice, and the mother of much
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:165914:10"/>perjury, and which three worthy members there, <hi>viz. Mr. Moyer, Mr. Barners,</hi> and <hi>Mr. Moor,</hi> in open Court cried ſhame on, but were overruled, by the influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of Sir <hi>Arthur</hi> (being the principal inſtrument of placing the ſaid Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners in their power) as your Petitioner by their dealings with him, having juſt cauſe to judge, hath more prevalency with them, then the rules of Juſtice and right, as in part may appear by the Copy of his Petition delivered unto them, hereunto annexed.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>The Premiſes conſidered, and for that your Petitioner hath now for almoſt two full years, been moſt injuriouſly, and arbitrarily thruſt out, and as unjuſtly kept out of his rightfull eſtate and poſſeſſion, (without ever having any pretence of title ſet up againſt him) the clear profit whereof by Sir</hi> Arthur Haſelrig<hi>'s own Certificate, amounts to</hi> 15 l. <hi>a day, and all that while no piece of a proof of the States Title offered or produced, and in regard Sir</hi> Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thur Haſelrig <hi>hath put certain of his Officers and Soldiers into the poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the ſaid Colemynes, which are but unskilfull Collyers, and (as your Petitioner is lately informed) do work the Mynes very foully and injuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, and are like to deſtroy them, and ſo will indanger your Petitioners utter undoing, in point of breach of Covenant with his Landlord,</hi> John Hedworth <hi>Eſquire, ſon and heir of the aforeſaid Sir</hi> John Hedworth, <hi>the Inheritor of the ſaid Mynes.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Your Petitioner therefore moſt humbly prays the Juſtice of the Parliament, that he may either be reſtored to his poſſeſſion upon good ſecurity given to the Parliament, to be anſwerable for the profits, in caſe hereafter the ſaid Mynes ſhall appear to be duely ſequeſtrable. Or otherwiſe that the Commiſſioners for compounding, may be commanded by your Order forth with to hear and determine the whole matter, and admit</hi> Wrays <hi>Depoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>itions in Chancery for evidence againſt himſelf; or elſe in caſe of fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther delay, that the ſaid Sir</hi> Arthur Haſelrig, <hi>and the other two that arbitrarily took away your Petitioners poſſeſſion with all thoſe Officers and Commanders of Sir</hi> Arthurs, <hi>that now poſſeſs and enjoy the profits of the ſaid Collyery, may forthwith be ordered and compelled by your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors, to give your Petitioner good ſecurity to anſwer him the profits of the ſaid Collyery, his dammages and expences, in caſe the ſaid Collyery be judged your Petitioners, or that you will declare that without the check or controul of this honourable Houſe, or the Committee of Indempni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, he may have his remedy at Law againſt the ſaid Sir</hi> Arthur, <hi>and all whatſoever under him, or that have joyned with him to act illegally, and arbitrarily againſt your Petitioner and his ſaid Tenants, and that you will take care to maintain the honor and dignity of Parliament (which doth conſiſt in doing Juſtice and right without reſpect of perſons) by dealing with Sir</hi> Arthur <hi>according to his demerit, in caſe your Petitioner ſhall fully make it appear to your Honors or ſome of your Committees, that Sir</hi> Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thur <hi>hath meerly acted arbitrarily, and without all ſhadow of Law or Juſtice, in taking your Petitioners right and propriety from him; himſelf, and his own privat gain and intereſt, being principally at the bottom of theſe his proceedings.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>And he ſhall pray, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Joſiah Primat.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <q>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:165914:10"/>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="petition">
                        <head>To the honourable the Commiſſioner for Compounding</head>
                        <head type="sub">The humble Petition of <hi>Joſiah Primatt,</hi> Citizen and Leather<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeller of <hi>London.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>Sheweth,</opener>
                        <p>THAT the Colliery of <hi>Harraton</hi> in the County of <hi>Durham,</hi> conſiſting of four Seams of Coal, diſtinguiſhed by the names of the half yard, three quarter, five quarter, and nine quarter ſeam of Coal, and that one moity of the five and nine quarter ſeams of Coal in the ſaid Colliery were wrought under your Petitioners title, one of them until 1640. and the other until 1642. and from that time, both the ſaid ſeams of Coals lay drowned and unwrought until 1647. at which time your Pettioners te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants <hi>(viz) Mr. George Lilburn</hi> and <hi>Mr. George Grey</hi> the younger, as to one moiety, and the tenants of one <hi>Commondale,</hi> and one <hi>Metcalf</hi> as to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther fourth part of the ſeams of coal, undertook to regain and work the ſaid 5. or 9. quarter ſeams of coals, and by the expence of neer 2000 <hi>l.</hi> they did regain and work the ſame until <hi>May</hi> 1648. at which time the mines were fired, and above 50. perſons lives loſt thereby, and within two monthes after by a flood, the ſaid mines were drowned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, and by the end of that year were regained again by the vaſt expence of your Petioners ſaid tennants, <hi>George Lilburne</hi> and <hi>George Grey,</hi> who enjoyed the ſame until <hi>September</hi> 1649. And within two moneths after were ſequeſtred by ſir <hi>Arthur Haſelrige,</hi> &amp;c. and by Souldiers violently ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from your Petitioners ſaid tenants, meerly ont of pretence that they were ſequeſtred in 1644. as belonging to one <hi>Thomas Wray</hi> of <hi>Beamiſh</hi> in in the ſaid County, a Papiſt Delinquent.</p>
                        <p>That before the day of ſequeſtration, your Petitioner went down in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the County of <hi>Durham,</hi> and by his Councel deſired the Committee there, that the ſaid <hi>Mr. Wray</hi> might ſhew hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> title, and evidence to the ſaid mines, or that any order in 1644. for ſequeſtring the ſame, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to the ſaid <hi>Mr. Wray,</hi> might be produced; but upon the day of hearing before the Committee of <hi>Durham,</hi> no ſuch order could be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced, and it would not be permitted by ſir <hi>Arthur Haſelrige</hi> that the ſaid <hi>Wray</hi> ſhould ſhew any title thereunto, as is already depoſed before your Honors, by divers witneſſes then preſent.</p>
                        <p>That your Petitioner thereupon appealed to your Honors, and after long attendance, comming to a hearing about the ſeven and twentieth of <hi>February</hi> laſt, the depoſition of the ſaid <hi>Wray</hi> in Chancery, not being allowed to be uſed, although in <hi>October</hi> 1641. he poſitively ſwore that he had no intereſt at all in the 5. and 9. quarter coal, but a fourth part; which oath in any Court in <hi>England,</hi> ought not to be denied for good evidence againſt himſelf, and the depoſitions of other witneſſes being laid aſide as parties, although they offered their oathes, that they had no intereſt therein in Law or equity, and there was no writing purpor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the ſame; Your Petitioner thereupon was neceſſitated to withdraw
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:165914:11"/>his Petition, and to preſent a new Petition according to your order, ſtating his title unto the 5. and 9. quarter ſeams of coal and his poſſeſſion thereof, and to ſend above two hundred miles for ſeveral witneſſes to prove the ſame; and your committee of <hi>Durham,</hi> and <hi>Mr. Eowle,</hi> were ordered to take a ſpecial care of the Common-wealths Intereſt therein, and <hi>Mr. Wray</hi> was ordered to be at the hearing, and to have monies al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed him for his charges, and to bring with him all his deeds and evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences concerning the ſame.</p>
                        <p>That your Petitioners witneſſes being examined, and according to your Order, publication had, and a report of the ſtate of the caſe being drawn by <hi>Mr. Reading,</hi> you were pleaſed to appoint a day for hearing the caſe, and to order that <hi>Mr. Wray</hi> ſhould be preſent at the ſame to produce his deeds, and evidences, and he not coming, a ſecond day of hearing was appointed, and the ſaid <hi>Wray</hi> ordered again to be there; and he not coming, it was pretended, that the reaſon was becauſe he had not a licence from the Councel of State to come to <hi>London,</hi> although your own Officers had for about two moneths been ordered to procure ſuch a licence, whereupon your Petitioner undertook to procure ſuch a licence, and in one afternoon did procure the ſame, and ſent it down by the Poſt.</p>
                        <p>That now the ſaid <hi>Wray</hi> having been come to <hi>London</hi> above a week, your Petitioner expected his hearing,, according to your ſeveral Orders, and that <hi>Mr. Wray</hi> ſhould have brought his evidences into Court; but in ſteed hereof on <hi>Friday</hi> laſt, he findes <hi>Mr. Wray</hi> Petitioning for three moneths longer time, but ſtates no title at all, nor produceth any deed according to your ſeveral Orders in the ſaid caſe, nor names any deed of any date, that he would have time to prove; and at laſt makes<note n="(*)">Whoſe oath is dated the <hi>27.</hi> of June <hi>1651.</hi>
                           </note> Oath that he hath material witneſs to examine, but names not unto what, and being asked who they were, he ſaid in open Court, he knew not; yet contrary to the rules of all Courts of Juſtice in <hi>England,</hi> that Affi-davit of the ſaid <hi>Wray</hi> was admitted by your honors, as ſufficient to give him a longer time.</p>
                        <p>That your Petitioner humbly offers it to you, that by confeſſion of all parties, you took the ſaid 5. and 9. quarter ſeams of coals out of your Petitioners poſſeſſion in 1649. and that in neer two years ſince, no proof is offered on the behalf of the State, that the State was ever in poſſeſſion of the ſaid ſeams of coal by ſequeſtration, which ought to have been up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on record, if it had been ſo, and that your Petitioner hath proved by many ſufficient witneſſes, that the 5. and 9. quarter ſeams of coal was never wrought, from 1642. till 1647. When they were won and wrought by your Petitioner and his tennants and others: claiming from <hi>Metcalf</hi> and <hi>Commondale;</hi> and that in ſuch caſes, by your own rules, you do take away no mans poſſeſſion, until the States title thereunto appears: And if it be doubtful, you ſuffer the Poſſeſſor to enjoy it upon ſecurity.</p>
                        <p>He further offers, That in caſe the ſaid 9. and 5. quarter ſeams of coal ſhould by ill management be drowned, fired, or the Pits wrought out, a vaſt ſum of money would not recover the ſame, and he knows not how he ſhall be repaired.</p>
                        <p>
                           <pb n="21" facs="tcp:165914:11"/>
                           <hi>He therefore humbly prays, That he may either be reſtored to his poſſeſſion, upon proof hereof, now before you, at leaſt upon ſecurity, which you do in ordinary Caſes, upon an Affidavit onely: Or otherwiſe that his Caſe may be heard forth with, no Title ever yet being ſet up againſt him.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>And your Petitioner ſhall ever pray, <hi>&amp;c. Joſiah Primatt.</hi>
                           </signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>And to make it further appear, that it was not the nine and five quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſeams of cole that was under the pretence of ſequeſtrations in 1644. but only the half yard and three quarter ſeams of coles; take a copy of an Order, made at <hi>Durham,</hi> the 13 of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> 1649. the Original I have by me, all writ with Maſter <hi>Gilpin</hi> the Clerks own hand.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="order">
                        <opener>
                           <dateline>
                              <hi>Dunelm.</hi> 
                              <date> Die Lunae 13 <hi>Augusti,</hi> 1649.</date> By the Committee of Sequeſtrations for this County.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>
                           <hi>VPon the hearing of the cauſe depending betwixt</hi> Thomas Wrey, George Lilburn, <hi>and</hi> George Grey <hi>Eſquires, touching the Colyeries at</hi> Harraton, <hi>it appeared to the ſaid Committee, that the half yard and three quarter Cole was wrought for the uſe of the ſaid Maſter</hi>
                           <note n="*">And yet I have ſeen two depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions taken by Maſter <hi>Cary,</hi> that contradicts this Order, and ſaith poſitively, that then one M. <hi>VVilli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am Fenwick</hi> of <hi>Harraton,</hi> farmed the ſaid half yard and three quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſeams of cole of Maſter <hi>VVrey,</hi> and wrought them upon his own accompt, and that Sir <hi>William Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, &amp;c.</hi> onely ſequeſtred <hi>Wrays</hi> rent of the ſaid ſmal ſeams, and by bargain and ſale bought divers 100 Chaldron of the ſaid coles of the ſaid <hi>Fenwick,</hi> for part of which he paid him ready money, and the reſt remains unpaid for at this day.</note> Wrey <hi>or his aſſignes, and for no other per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in the year</hi> 1644. <hi>and that in the ſame year the ſaid Colyery was ſeque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred by Sir</hi> William Armyn <hi>for the uſe of the State, and the ſaid Seque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration was not at any time ſince taken off. It is therefore thought fit, and ſo ordered by the ſaid Committee, that all the ſaid parties ſhall produce their wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings and evidences, touching their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral titles and claims, either from Maſter</hi> Primate <hi>of</hi> London, <hi>or any other perſon, and their ſeveral witneſſes to be examined by the ſaid Committee upon</hi> Tueſday <hi>the eleventh day of</hi> Sep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tember <hi>next coming. And that the preſent tenants or occupiers of the ſaid Colyeries, ſhall continue the working of the ſaid Colyeries in the mean time as tenants to the State: And that Lieutenant</hi> Edward Shepherdſon <hi>ſhall forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with enter unto the ſaid Colyery, and take poſſeſſion thereof, for the uſe of the State, till the title ſhall be determined and tried, and ſhall take true and perfect ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt of all the Coles that are or ſhall be wrought in the ſaid Colyeries, and of all the charges and diſburſments to be laid out and diſourſed in the working thereof, during that time. And the ſaid Lieutenant</hi> Edward Shepherdſon <hi>to have ſuch reaſonable allowance for his pains, as this Committee ſhall think fit.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>Vera Copia Ex. Per me <hi>Iſaa. Gilpin</hi> Cl. Com.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>And becauſe by a Member of Parliament, that was by in the Speakers Chamber the other day, I am credibly informed that Maſter <hi>Winſlow</hi> was with the Speaker there, and endeavored very much to render my Unckle and M. <hi>George Grey</hi> to be two baſe fellows, according to the contents of the ſaid falſe and unjuſt Certificate of the foreſaid pretended Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee of <hi>Durham;</hi> and ſaid what elſe of him he pleaſed, and indeavo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red very much to reprorch me by accaſing me of indeavouring
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:165914:12"/>to divide the Army amongſt themſelves, and the Parliament amongſt themſelves; and now the Commiſſioners amongſt themſelves, by ſetting three againſt four, and that it was a falſe averment of us, to ſay there was publication in the caſe. I ſhall therefore diſprove that fully, only I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire this may be obſerved, that Maſter <hi>Cary</hi> your Examinor upon our laſt Petition, examined all our witneſſes upon interrogatories, and it was your Order that commanded our depoſitions out of his hands; which Order compared with your other Orders for three ſeveral days of hearing, is ſufficient with another that either is, or ought in your Books to be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred to prove there was publication in the caſe: but before I come to that, let me tell you it is but a poor guilty ſhift to put off the reading of Maſter <hi>Primates</hi> Petition, becauſe either <hi>George Lilburn, George Grey,</hi> or <hi>Iohn Lilburn,</hi> is ſo and ſo; therefore it is not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t to read Maſter <hi>Primats</hi> Petition, and to do him juſtice and right: for Maſter <hi>Primats</hi> Petition is either true or falſe, and you have either do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e him injuſtice, or you have not; however let us come to a fair and equal hearing. And I do here aver, I dare ingage my life to prove the whole Petition againſt you, but ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing you have by your daily reproaches put me to it, by calling my Vnckle cheat, &amp;c. at your open Table upon <hi>Thurſday</hi> laſt in the caſe of the Lady <hi>Tong;</hi> I do aver that you are four of the moſt unjuſteſt, and unworthieſt men, that ever the Parliament made in one place Judges in <hi>England;</hi> and that you are fit for nothing but to be ſpewed out of all humane ſociety, by all ingenious rational men; and that for the injuſtice you have acted, and the diſhonour you have done the Parliament in your places, you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve a ſharper and ſeverer puniſhment from them then King <hi>Alfred</hi> gave to thoſe forty four Judges he hanged in one year for their injuſtice, whoſe petty crimes in compariſon of yours, are recorded at the latter end of the Law Book, called the <hi>Mirror of Iuſtice;</hi> you deſerving for example ſake, (all circumſtances conſidered) rather to have your skins flead over your ears, and ſtopt full of ſtraw, and hung up in ſome publique place, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter others from doing that multiplied groſſe wickedneſs that you have committed in a ſhort time; and ſo now I come to your forementioned Order, the copy of which thus followeth.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="order">
                        <head>By the Commiſſioners for compounding, &amp;c. 28 <hi>Martis,</hi> 1651.</head>
                        <p>VPon motion made by <hi>M. John Lilburn,</hi> alledging that <hi>M Joſiah Primat</hi> hath ſeverall witneſſes in Town, which can give teſtimony concerning the Colyery of <hi>Harraton,</hi> and deſires that the ſaid witneſſes may be ſpeedily exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned here in Town. It is ordered that <hi>M. Fowle</hi> do examine the ſaid witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes by this day ſeven-night.<note n="*">And upon the expiration of this Order, Major <hi>Iohn Wildman</hi> in open Court made a motion for publica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the depoſitions, unto which Maſter <hi>Fowles</hi> Solicitor for the State in open court conſented unto, upon which by ſpecial order, there was publication, which if not entred in your Books, the fault is none of ours.</note> And in caſe that the ſaid witneſſes ſhall be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained longer in Town on behalf of the State, that then their charges expen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in ſuch ſtay, be allowed unto them. And it is referred to <hi>M. Reading</hi> after ſuch examinations taken, to peruſe the ſame, and alſo the Petition of the ſaid <hi>M. Primate,</hi> and Report the caſe.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>Vera copia Ex. T. Baly,</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>The forementioned Orders for hearing the cauſe thus followeth.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:165914:12"/>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="order">
                        <head>By the Commiſſioners for compounding, &amp;c. 22. <hi>May</hi> 1651.</head>
                        <p>WHereas we ordered <hi>21</hi> may current, That the Caſe touching the Coliery at <hi>Harraton</hi> ſhould be <hi>heard on Thurſday then next come fortnight</hi> unleſſe Mr <hi>Fowle</hi> ſhewed cauſe to the contrary by Wedneſday then next. Now up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the deſire of Mr. <hi>Fowle</hi> on behalf of the Common-wealth, that there may bee longer time given for the hearing of the ſaid cauſe; and that Mr. <hi>Wray</hi> might according to former order, be ſent for up to be preſent at that time, <hi>with what E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence he hath in his hands,</hi> touching the ſame: It is ordered that the ſaid Caſe be heard on this day three weekes, unleſſe juſt cauſe be ſhewed to the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. And Mr. <hi>Wray</hi> is required at the time to attend here and bring with him all the Evidences and Writings in his hands concerning the ſaid Coliery, and that he have timely notice thereof. And the Commiſſioners for Sequeſtrations in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Durham,</hi> are to certifie to <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s ſuch notice the week after the receipt hereof, and pay to the ſaid Mr. <hi>Wray 5.</hi> l. for and towards his charges. And that Mr. <hi>Fowle</hi> doe attend the right Honorable the Lord Preſident of the Councel of State, for a licence for the ſaid Mr. <hi>Wray</hi> to come up to <hi>London</hi> accordingly, he being a Papiſt and Delinquent.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>Copia vera exam. T. Bayly.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                     <div type="order">
                        <head>By the Commiſſioners for compounding. 5. <hi>Junii</hi> 1651.</head>
                        <p>WHereas we ordered <hi>22</hi> May laſt, That the Caſe touching the Coliery at <hi>Harraton</hi> in the County of <hi>Durham,</hi> ſhould be heard on that day three weekes, unleſſe cauſe were ſhewed to the contrary. And Mr. <hi>Wray</hi> required to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend here at that time, and to bring with him all the Evidences and Writings in his hands concerning the ſaid Coliery, and to have timely notice thereof. And the Commiſſioners for Sequeſtrations in the County of <hi>Durham,</hi> were to cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie ſuch notice to <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s the week after the receipt of the ſaid Order, and to pay the ſaid Mr. <hi>Wray 5.</hi> l. for and towards his charges. And that Mr <hi>Fowle</hi> ſhould at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend the right Honorable the Lord Preſident of the Councell of State for a licence for the ſaid <hi>Wray</hi> to come up to <hi>London</hi> accordingly, he being a Papiſt and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquent. Now for that upon information given to <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s by Mr. <hi>Fowle,</hi> that hee hath not as yet procured a licence from the Councel of State for the ſaid M. <hi>Wrays</hi> coming hither at the day of hearing aforeſaid; and upon conſideration had thereof, and the ſhort ſpace of time now remaining for the ſaid Mr. <hi>Wray</hi> to come up hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the three weeks for hearing the ſaid Caſe being farre ſpent, ſo that we have not time to addreſſe our ſelves to the Councell of State for a licence for the ſaid Mr. <hi>Wray:</hi> It is therefore reſolved, and ſo ordered, That the ſaid Mr. <hi>Wray</hi> doe forthwith upon notice hereof, repaire hither, and bring with him all the Writings and Evidences in his hands touching the ſaid Coliery, to be preſent at the hearing of the ſaid Caſe: and for which this ſhall be his ſufficient Warrant. And it is further ordered, That the Commiſſioners for Sequeſtrations in the ſaid County of <hi>Durham,</hi> doe forthwith pay unto the ſaid Mr. <hi>Wray</hi> the ſumme of five pounds for and towards his charges, &amp;c.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>
                              <hi>Copia vera exam. T.</hi> Bayly.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>But to return back, the ſaid Sir <hi>Arthur Haſterig</hi> fell upon my Vnkle, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the Land he farms at <hi>Ford,</hi> as if he had cozened and cheated the State there, and hath put him to a great deale of trouble and charge thereby, although he juſtly farmd it of thoſe that had a right to Le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> it.
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:165914:13"/>the main drift of ſir <hi>Arthur,</hi> to my underſtanding, being to get al that land of <hi>Ford,</hi> with all other lands of the late Baron <hi>Hiltons</hi> that he gave to the poor of <hi>London,</hi> &amp;c. inveſted in the preſent Col. <hi>Hilton</hi> a delinquent, that ſo he might by himſelf, ragents, get him put into the Bil of Sale, being a gallant and fit parcel of Land (lying cloſe by <abbr>Eſq</abbr> 
               <hi>Hedworths</hi>) for Sir <hi>Arthur</hi> to purchaſe at the hands of the State, after the Rate of his owne ſurveying, and add M. <hi>Hallimans</hi> Ballaſt key and Land at <hi>Munckwarmouth</hi> near <hi>Sunderland,</hi> if Sir <hi>Arthur</hi> could get that made to be (as he ſtrongly endeavours it) <hi>Pudſeys,</hi> the Delinquents, it would be fit for the Bil of ſale alſo: And ſo Sir <hi>Arthur</hi> in time might have a fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ing even from the ſpring of the River Wear, to its going into the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, for I am ſure lately Sir <hi>Arthur</hi> came to plead his cauſe againſt poor <hi>Halliman</hi> which hee did with that violence that I never heard man in life do, &amp; he declared him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in my hearing, that the land claimd by <hi>Halliman</hi> was juſt and fit to be put into the Bill of ſale.</p>
            <p>Another of Sir <hi>Arthurs</hi> unjuſt dealings with my Vncle, is his going about to make him a deceiver, and the cheater of the State about the Colliery of <hi>Lamton,</hi> in which I am confident he dealt as juſtly and as ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly as any Tenant in <hi>England</hi> could doe that took ſuch a thing of any man for a valuable conſideration, that had a right to let it.</p>
            <p>Another piece of ſir <hi>Arthurs</hi> dealing with my Vnkle, was in his ſeque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtring that Land he had in mortgage from the Lady <hi>Tonge</hi> for 600 <hi>l.</hi> in redy money to pay her ſons Compoſition, as if he had by ſo doing com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted the horribleſt cheat againſt the State that poſſibly could be but M. <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eretons</hi> Report, and your own Order made upon Thurſday laſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the 24 July, 1651. hath ſufficiently cleared my Vnkle for an honeſt man in that particular, although M. <hi>Mollins</hi> at the beginning of the cauſ could with open mouth in the Court call it a notorious cheat, which was reproved by Major <hi>Wildman,</hi> by demanding of him if he were not aſhamed to condemn a thing before he heard it, or underſtood it; but it ſeems Sir <hi>Arthur</hi> had ſaid it, and left his commands with him ſo to cal it: and therefore right or wrong he muſt believe it and obey it: and M <hi>Winſloe,</hi> and M. <hi>Squib</hi> both did their parts to that purpoſe, but truth and the reaſon of M. <hi>Moyer</hi> was too ſtrong for you all three.</p>
            <p>Another piece of Sir <hi>Arthur Haſelrig</hi> moſt falſe and wicked dealing with my Uncle, was at Haberdaſhers hall, not long ſince, when he and I had the tug for 5 or 6 houres together hand to hand, where he would have had you to have paſt ſentence upon my Vncle upon 3, or 4 verball charges of his, proſecuted with that heat by him, as if it had laid upon his life, which were all falſhoods and lyes in themſelves, and for a taſte of one for all give me leave to whet up your memories, that when Sir <hi>Arthur</hi> came to tax my Uncle for cheating of the State of the profits of the land of <hi>Harraton,</hi> as wel as of the coliery, which was ſequeſtred only for the Delinquency of the foreſaid <hi>Thomas Wray,</hi> as he aver'd, being all
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:165914:13"/>of it his and he or you the Commiſſioners demanded my Vncles anſwer unto it, which I gave to this purpoſe, that we denyed every thing that Sir Arthur ſaid there, being nothing but falſhoods and untruths in all his averments; and put it upon him to prove what he ſaid: at which he being very mad, that ſuch a man of his rank and quality as he was, &amp; one who had from the Parliament ſo great a truſt upon him, ſhould be ſo affronted as he was, by ſuch a man as I was; unto which I replyed to this purpoſe, That ſetting aſide his authority, with which I would make no compariſons, I judg my ſelf as honeſt and as good a man as himſelf, and come of as good parentage as he; and if he or the greateſt man in <hi>England</hi> durſt go about in my hearing to make my Father and his gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration a company of knaves and cheaters (as he that day had done) in things or for things, for which my conſcience told me they had don no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but juſtly &amp; honeſtly, I ſhould not judg my ſelf worthy to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted to com from the loyns of ſo honeſt &amp; juſt a man as my Father was, if I ſhould hear him ſo baſely abuſed to his face, as he had abuſed him, and ſuffer it in ſilence; for he hinted as if my Father and Vncle had defrauded or loſt unto the State 12000. a year of ſequeſtred lands; and that my Father had made himſelf rich by medling with ſequeſtred lands, and therfore if he durſt abuſe my Father in things I knew to be falſe, I durſt tell him he ſpoke falſly in any place in <hi>England;</hi> and therefore if he would not by me bee told of his falſhoods, let him ſpeak truth But Sir <hi>Arthur</hi> at that time began to lift up his eyes and hands, and call for ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance from Heaven, averring upon his ſoul, his conſcience &amp; honor, &amp; calling the grear Lord God of heaven and earth to bear witneſs, that he ſpoke nothing but Truth; and that as ever he expected to appear with comfort before the Lord, the land of <hi>Harraton,</hi> which <abbr>Eſq</abbr> 
               <hi>Hedworth</hi> lays claim to, was M, <hi>Wrays,</hi> and was ſequeſtred for his delinquency, and his only and alone; and this I know, ſaith he; you have a Certificate of from your own ſworn commiſſioners, who are men of honor and conſcience, and therefore deſired it might be read; Of which Certificate, and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers about that land, I was totally ignorant of, and had never ſeen not heard read before, to my knowledg; and M. <hi>Baily</hi> the Clerk being com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to read it, he read a Certificate, the copy of which thus follows</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="certificate">
                        <p>
                           <hi>Gentlemen,</hi> we formerly returned that we had ſequeſtred the Lands at <hi>Harraton</hi> for the Recuſancy of the Lady <hi>Dorothy Hedworth,</hi> the relict of Sir <hi>John Hedworth</hi> deceaſed. And we perceiving by ſeveral Orders ſent unto us, that <hi>John Hedworth</hi> 
                           <abbr>Eſq</abbr> ſon of the ſaid Sir <hi>John Hedworth</hi> and the ſaid Lady, is endevoring a pretended right thereunto, to get off the Sequeſtration; we have therefore ſent the depoſitions incloſed with a copy of a deed which holds forth the Ladies intereſt, and the originall deed being in the cuſtody of Mr. <hi>Levet,</hi> or Mr. <hi>George Gray,</hi> who now live and recide at <hi>London,</hi> we have ſent what teſtimony was produced unto us by the ſaid Lady <hi>Derothy Hedworth,</hi> and deſire that Mr. <hi>Levet</hi> and Mr. <hi>Gray</hi> aforeſaid may be called before you, and injoyned to produce the ſaid Original deed, whereof this incloſed is a Copy, in caſe the State be prejudiced by taking off the ſequeſtration of the ſaid eſtate, by deſtroying the Ladies title, which determins not until her death: We remain.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <dateline>
                              <hi>Durham</hi> 
                              <date>
                                 <hi>April</hi> 18. 1651.</date>
                           </dateline>
                           <signed>Gentlemen, your aſſured friends; <hi>Francaes Wren, Thomas Delavel.</hi>
                           </signed>
                           <signed>Copia vera. Exam. John Leech.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:165914:14"/>At the reading of which you may remember Sir <hi>Arthur</hi> was full of rage at the Cleark, but I helpt to ſtop his mouth a little, by appealing to you to be Judges whether there was either conſcience, honor, faith or truth in Sir <hi>Arthur Haſelrig,</hi> or that there was any credit to be given to any thing he had ſaid or ſworn, ſeeing he had ſo ſolemnly averred, proteſted, and impre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated, and cal'd God to witneſs, that the land was ſequeſtred onely and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone for Mr. <hi>Wrays</hi> Delinquency; and his own Record that he firſt produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to prove his aſſertion, ſaith the quite contrary; but although I then plyd him with hot cloaths, and made him in the face as read as a Turkey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cock, yet he was not totally daſht out of Countenance; but to mend the matter, called for another Certificate, ſaying he was ſure there was ſuch a Certificate as he ſpake of; which being before the Gleark, it was read: The Copie of which thus followeth.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="certificate">
                        <p>Gentlemen, According to your Order granted upon the motion of Mr. <hi>Higgins,</hi> in the behalf of <hi>John Hedworth</hi> Eſquire of <hi>Harraton</hi> and <hi>William Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyman</hi> of <hi>Monkewarmonth,</hi> dated <hi>July</hi> 12. 1650. We do hereby certifie that concerning the Lands in <hi>Harraton,</hi> pretended by <hi>John Hedworth</hi> to have been in his poſſeſſion for ſeveral years laſt paſt: It appears to us, that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout <hi>May</hi>-day 1647. the ſaid lands were ſequeſtred by the Committee of Sequeſtrations for the County, as belonging unto <hi>Thomas Wray</hi> of <hi>Beamiſh</hi> Eſquire, he being then in the ſole poſſeſſion thereof, and ſo having had the poſſeſſion for many years, and that they were letten by the Committee to ſeveral Farmours for 200 <hi>l per annum,</hi> and that Mr. <hi>George Gray,</hi> one of the ſaid Committee, dealt with the ſaid Farmours, and got into the poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of the ſaid lands, and ſo continued for ſeveral years together, not paying, any rent to the State. And that when the Committee about a year ſince called for their rent, and the arrears, Mr. <hi>Gray</hi> then ſtood up and clai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med the ſaid lands, as belonging to one <hi>John Hedworth,</hi> that married his daughter by collour of an intail, pretended to have been made by ſome of <hi>Hedworths</hi> Anceſtors.</p>
                        <p>The Committee then finding the ſtate had been ſo long diſpoſed without any Order, and that by a member of their own Committee, and that it did belong to the State from the year 1644. that being the time that Mr. <hi>Wray</hi> was ſequeſtred as a Papiſt in Arms, they ordered the ſaid lands to be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtred and diſpoſed for the uſe of the State: And whereas Mr. <hi>Hedworth</hi> informs you that he was in poſſeſſion for diverſe years paſt, and that we put him out, the truth is, the State was long ſince in poſſeſſion, the land be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to Mr. <hi>Wray,</hi> and he being ſequeſtred in the year 1644. and Mr. <hi>Wray</hi> has now a good eſtate in it. But Mr. <hi>Gray</hi> by vertue of that power as aforeſaid, gets into the poſſeſſion as under-tenant to the State, pays no rent, and after marries his daughter to Mr <hi>Hedworths</hi> and then alſo taking the profits to his own uſe; and when the Committee demanded rent and arrears of him, then held forth a Title in Mr. <hi>Hedworths</hi> name: And had not the land been long ſince in the poſſeſſion of the State, we ſhould not have turned <hi>Hedworth</hi> out of poſſeſſion, but onely ſtaid the profits, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted you with it, and ſo we ſhall do in all caſes of the like nature; but we hold it very fit and neceſſary, that where the State hath been poſſeſſed,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:165914:14"/>they ought not to be put out of poſſeſſion by any privat or clandeſtine way; but either publickly by Authority from you the Commisſioners, or the Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rons of the Exchequer, or by leave given from one of you to the plaintiff, to ſue at common Law, care being taken that the States Title be defended; and we offer it to you, if it be not requiſite that Mr. <hi>Gray</hi> be called to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count for the profits of theſe lands, which of due and right he ought to pay to the State. And as for <hi>Monk-Warmouth</hi> Hal, it was ſequeſtred in the year 1644. from one <hi>Ralph Pudſey</hi> a Papiſt in Arms, he being then in the poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſesſion of it, the aforeſaid Mr. <hi>Gray</hi> being a Committee-man, took it of the Committee, and being then poſſeſſed of it, never paid rent to the State, and when he ſaw his time, he let <hi>Hollyman</hi> have the poſſesſion of the land, and took to himſelf the Ballace Shore, and ſo the State was deceived of both, and <hi>Hollyman</hi> by pretending a Title by marrying one of <hi>Robert Widdringtons</hi> daughters; <hi>Pudſey</hi> being then, and ſo continues ſtill in Arms againſt us, the ſaid <hi>Hollyman</hi> commencing a ſuit againſt <hi>Pudſey,</hi> pretending his wives Title to be better then <hi>Pudſeys,</hi> and there being none to defend the Title, he hath gotten ſome legall collour, and ſo thinks utterly to diſpoſſeſs the State of their Intereſt; and this is the truth of <hi>Hollymans</hi> Caſe: And we offer it like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, whether Mr. <hi>Gray</hi> ſhall not give an account to the State for the profits of this, as for the other.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>
                              <list>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>Arthur Haſelrig.</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>Francs Wren.</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>Thomas Delavall.</hi>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </signed>
                           <date>
                              <hi>Auguſt.</hi> 8. 1651.</date>
                           <signed>Copid vera Exam. Dunelm. Jo. Leech.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>After the reading which, you may remember I told you to this purpoſe, that Sir <hi>Arthur</hi> had mended the matter wel; for he had now made his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners as bad as himſelfe: nay, he had made them knaves and forſworn men upon Record; Foraſmuch as they are upon their Oathes, and yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn certificates point blank croſſe to one another. I then deſired you to conſider whether there were any truth in thoſe Commiſſioners, or any faith or credit to be given to any thing they ſay or ſweare. And yet notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding all this, I will ſhew you the copy of a third certificate or Order in the ſame thing, various from both the former, which thus followeth.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="order">
                        <head>By the Commiſſioners for Sequeſtration. <hi>March the 21. 1649.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                           <salute>Dunelm</salute>
                        </opener>
                        <p>IT is ordered, That <hi>William Brewing</hi> Gent. Solicitor for Sequeſtration, ſhall forthwith repaire to <hi>Harraton,</hi> and take poſſeſſion for the uſe of the State of all thoſe lands and Coliery in <hi>Harraton,</hi> now under Sequeſtration, for the recuſancy of the Lady <hi>Hedworth.</hi> and for the Recuſancy and Delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quency of <hi>Thomas Wray</hi> and <hi>Ralph Rooksby,</hi> together with all the Gins and other Engins ſtanding upon the grounds, for the working of the ſaid Colie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry late in the poſſeſſion of Mr. <hi>George Lilburne</hi> and Mr. <hi>George Grey,</hi> untill they ſhall plead their Title before the Barons of the Exchequer, and give ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count to the State for the profits of the ſaid coliery.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>Copia vera exam. Cuthbert Hawdon. Clerk to the ſaid Commiſſioners.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>And if any obſervations upon their contradictions be not authentick e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to declare them contradictions to you, take the copie of your owne Order made that very day in the caſe, which thus followeth.</p>
            <q>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:165914:15"/>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="order">
                        <head>By the Commiſſioners for compounding, &amp;c. <hi>30 April 1651.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>VPon reading of two certificares returned from the Commiſſioners for Sequeſtration for the county of <hi>Durham,</hi> the one dated 8 Auguſt 1650. The other dated 8 April currant, touching the lands of <hi>Harraton</hi> in the ſaid county, betwixt which there ſeems to us to be ſome contradiction touching the perſons for who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſame was ſequeſtred: it is reſolved that copies of both the ſaid certificates be ſent down to the ſaid Commiſſioners, who are to certifie unto us how the ſaid contradiction happeneth, and they are to ſearch the Books and Records of the former Committee, whether Mr. <hi>Wray</hi> was not in poſſeſſion of the ſaid lands at the time of the firſt ſequeſtration there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; and they are to examine witneſſes touching the ſame, and what profits hath been received out of the ſaid lands ſince the ſequeſtration, &amp; by whom. And they are to examine witneſſes upon Oath (if deſired) on behalf of Mr. <hi>George Lilburne</hi> and Mr. <hi>Geo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>ge Grey,</hi> or either of them, and to croſs examine the witneſſes on both ſides (if deſired) &amp; to return the proofs and examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to us ſealed up within ſix weeks next eaſuing: Mr. <hi>Fowles</hi> is to draw up a charge againſt Mr. <hi>Grey</hi> out of the certificate ſent up hither from the ſaid Commiſsioners in the county of <hi>Durham.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>
                              <hi>Copia vera exam.</hi> T. Bayly.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>Which Order having been ſerved upon the Commiſsioners of the county of <hi>Durham</hi> with ſeverall others about the lands of the ſaid <hi>Harraton,</hi> yet they wil obey none of them, but keep the ſaid lands from the right owner of them Eſquire <hi>John Hedworth,</hi> although he hath proved that he was in poſſeſsion when they ſequeſtred it, ſometimes for ones delinquency, ſometimes for ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers And that he was in poſſeſsion, take theſe proofs.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="testimony">
                        <head>
                           <hi>Witneſſes examined in the caſe of</hi> John Hedworth, <hi>Eſquire.</hi> 
                           <date>13. <hi>Feb.</hi> 1650.</date>
                        </head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>John Clifton</hi> of <hi>Gateſhhead</hi> in the County of <hi>Durham</hi> gentleman, ſworn and examined, being demanded who was in poſſesſion of the lands at <hi>Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raton,</hi> now ſequeſtred at the time of the ſeiſure made; ſaith that Mr. <hi>John Hedworth</hi> was at the time of Sequeſtration actually poſſeſſed of the lands at <hi>Harraton,</hi> and that ſince he knew the ſaid Mr. <hi>Hedworth,</hi> he hath frequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the Church, and was never in any ſervice againſt the Parliament.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>John Clifton.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                     <div type="testimony">
                        <p>
                           <hi>Thomas Petty</hi> of the City of <hi>Durham</hi> Apothecary, ſworne and examined, ſaith, That Mr. <hi>John Hedworth</hi> was in actual poſſesſion of the lands at <hi>Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raton,</hi> now ſequeſtred at the time of the laſt ſeiſure, for that to this exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants knowledge, he tilled the ground and ſtockt it; and that the ſaid <hi>John Hedworth</hi> was neither recuſant nor Delinquent to his knowledge.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>
                              <list>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>Capt. Coram</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>Thomas Delavell</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>Frances Wren.</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>Thomes Pettie.</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>T. Bayly.</hi>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </signed>
                           <hi>Copia vera Exam.</hi>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>Some of the Copies of the forementioned Orders for his land thus followeth.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="order">
                        <p>
                           <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> By the Commisſioners for compounding, <hi>&amp;c. July</hi> 12. 1650. Upon motion of Mr. <hi>Higgins</hi> in the behalf of <hi>John Hedworth</hi> of <hi>Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raton</hi> in the County of <hi>Durham</hi> Eſquire, and <hi>William Hollyman</hi> of <hi>Munck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>war mouth</hi> in the ſaid County, complaining, that whereas the before na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:165914:15"/>
                           <hi>Hedworth,</hi> hath had the poſſesſion of divers lands there for ſeverall years laſt paſt, by vertue of a deed made by his Anceſters in the 41 year of the Queen, and that the ſaid <hi>William Hollyman</hi> doth hold the moiety of the Mannor of <hi>Munck Warmouth</hi> in the right of his wife, which they have held for theſe ſeveral years; yet the Commisſioners for Sequeſtration have turned them out of poſſesſion, notwithſtanding they offered ſecrity to be reſponſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for the profits of the ſaid eſtate, upon pretence that the eſtate belongs to delinquents and papiſts. It is ordered &amp; the Commisſioners for ſequeſtration in the ſaid County, are hereby deſired to examin who was in poſſesſion at the time of their Sequeſtring the ſaid eſtate; And if the ſaid <hi>Hedworth</hi> &amp; <hi>Hollyman</hi> were in the actual poſſeſſion thereof, and be not Delinquents nor recuſants, That then they be reſtored to the poſſeſſion taken from them, giving ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to be reſponſible for the profits of the eſtate to which they ſhall be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored; And in the mean time, the ſaid Commiſſioners are to certifie the whole matter to this Committee: And that the ſaid <hi>Hedwo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>th</hi> and <hi>Hollyman</hi> proſecute the ſame to a Judgement here within the ſpace of three months.</p>
                        <trailer>
                           <hi>To the Commiſſioners for Sequeſtrations in the County of</hi> Durham.</trailer>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>
                              <list>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>Exam</hi> Jo. Leech.</item>
                                 <item>Jo. Berners.</item>
                                 <item>William Mollins.</item>
                                 <item>Edward Winſloe.</item>
                                 <item>Richard Moore.</item>
                              </list>
                           </signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>But before I inſert any more copies of your Orders, I ſhall here give you two of Mr. <hi>Hedworths</hi> Affidavits in the caſe, the copies of which thus follows.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="affidavit">
                        <p>
                           <hi>John Hedworth</hi> of <hi>Harraton</hi> in the County of <hi>Durham</hi> Eſquire maketh Oath, That he hath had the poſſeſſion of divers lands in <hi>Harraton</hi> aforeſaid, which he held to him and his heirs males of his body, by vertue of a deed made from his great Grandfather bearing date the 41 year of Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> and that he kept and had the ſaid lands in his poſſeſſion for theſe 3 years laſt paſt; until in <hi>March</hi> laſt the Commiſſioners for ſequeſtrations, put him out of poſſeſſion, upon pretence that part of the ſaid lands did belong to the Lady <hi>Hedworth</hi> his mother a recuſant, and the other lands did belong to <hi>Thomas Wray,</hi> and <hi>Ralph Rookesby</hi> delinquents; and this deponent demanding a Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificate of the cauſe of ſequeſtration, the Commiſſioners refuſed to let him have any; but took the poſſeſſion of his eſtate from him, notwithſtanding that he profered good ſecurity to be reſponſible for the profits of the ſaid lands, in caſe any pretended title ſhould be made good againſt his title; which is great dan mage to him, by reaſon that his cattel are unprovided for, and that his corn upon the ground may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>er much by the ill loooking thereunto.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <dateline>
                              <hi>Juram corum Commiſſarium</hi> 
                              <date>5. <hi>June.</hi> 1650.</date>
                           </dateline>
                           <signed>John Hedworth</signed>
                           <signed>Examined according to order the ſame day by <hi>Pet. Brereton.</hi>
                           </signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>The Copy of his ſaid ſecond Affidavit thus folleweth:</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="affidavit">
                        <p>
                           <hi>Iohn Hedworth</hi> of <hi>Harraton</hi> in the county of <hi>Durham</hi> Eſquire, maketh oath, that upon the ſixth day of <hi>Auguſt</hi> laſt, this deponent did deliver an Order from the Honorable the Commiſſioners for compounding with Delinquents to the Commiſſioners for ſequeſtration of the ſaid county, which Order was, that this deponent ſhould have the poſſeſſion of his lands, ſequeſtred from him by the ſaid Commiſſioners, this deponent gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſecurity to be reſponſal to the State for the mean profits, in caſe that the lands ſhould be adjudged againſt this deponent. As alſo by the ſaid Order the ſaid Commiſſioners were to certifie the cauſe of ſequeſtring the ſaid lands. And who was in poſſeſſion of the ſaid lands at the time of their ſequeſtration. This deponent maketh oath, that according to the ſaid Order, he did render good ſecurity, but the ſaid Commiſſioners refuſed to take any ſecurity, or to deliver him the poſſeſſion of the ſaid
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:165914:16"/>lands, according to the ſaid Order; but then ſaid that they would cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie the Commiſſioners for Compoſitions accordingly, but as yet this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponent cannot learn of any return made by them, although he hath wai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted above a month, and daily made inquiry for the ſame.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <dateline>
                              <hi>Jur. Coram Commiſſ.</hi> 
                              <date>11 <hi>Octob.</hi> 1650.</date>
                           </dateline>
                           <signed>John Hedworth.</signed>
                           <signed>
                              <hi>W. Molins. Copia vera exam.</hi> Jo. Leech.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>Vpon this laſt Affidavit, another Order was procured, the copy of which followeth.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="order">
                        <head>By the Commiſſioners for Compounding, &amp;c. <hi>die veneris 18 Oct. 1650.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>Vpon reading of an order of the 12 of <hi>July</hi> laſt 1650. and alſo the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of <hi>John Hedworth</hi> of <hi>Harraton,</hi> in the county of <hi>Durham,</hi> Eſquire, thereunto annexed, taken 11 <hi>Octob.</hi> inſtant. It is ordered, that a copy of the ſaid depoſition be ſent to the Commiſſioners for ſequeſtrations in the county of <hi>Durham,</hi> who are hereby required to certifie according to the ſaid Order of the 12 of <hi>July</hi> 1650. and that the ſaid <hi>John Hedworth</hi> do proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute his claim within a month.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>
                              <hi>Copia vera Exam. per Ia. Hind.</hi>
                              <list>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>Ia. Ruſſel.</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>Io. Berners.</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>Sam. Moyer.</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>Edw. Winſlo.</hi>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>But nothing being done upon this order, I upon the 5 <hi>Feb.</hi> laſt, mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved for our poſſeſſion, upon which they made another Order; the copy of which thus followeth.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="order">
                        <head>By the Commiſſioners for Compounding, &amp;c. <hi>5 Feb. 1650.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>Vpon reading of our Order made the 12 of <hi>Iuly</hi> 1650. in the caſe of <hi>Iohn Hedworth</hi> of <hi>Harraton</hi> in the county of <hi>Durham</hi> Eſquire. It is ordered that our ſaid Order be performed, and that the ſaid M. <hi>Hedworth</hi> ſhall be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>payed ſuch rents as appear to have been received our of his eſtate by the Commiſſioners in the country, ſince the date of the ſaid Order in caſe the cauſe ſhall be adjudged for him. And that the ſaid Commiſſioners do certifie unto us all their proceedings touching the ſaid M. <hi>Hedworths</hi> goods or lands within three weeks after notice hereof, that he may not be delayed any longer.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>
                              <hi>Copia vera Int.</hi> 387. <hi>exam.</hi>
                              <list>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>Io. Leech.</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>Rich. Moore.</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>Will. Molins.</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>Sam. Moyer.</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>Edw. Winſlo.</hi>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>Now unto your dealings with us about the colyery of <hi>Harraton,</hi> and to the land there, add to them your dealings with us about the Eſquires <hi>Cat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tel,</hi> and it will I think clearly appear to any rational man that you have ſold or given up your ſelves to be Sir <hi>Arthurs</hi> vaſſals and ſlaves, and that we ſhall have no effectual juſtice at your hands in any caſes, wherein he is concerned as he is in all theſe, becauſe it is againſt his will and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and becauſe by his cruſhing, and do as much as in him lieth, grinding to pieces poor Eſquire <hi>Hedworth,</hi> he will ſufficiently (as he may imagine) terrifie and affright any man in the county of <hi>Durham,</hi> to be familiar with a <hi>Lilburn,</hi> yea or ſo much as by buying or ſelling with him, and what your dealing with us hath been in the caſe of Eſquire <hi>Hedworths Cattel,</hi> may be briefly given you in the copy of his Petition, which he and I cauſed to be delivered in print at the Parliament door to the Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers thereof the very next day after M. <hi>Primat</hi> delivered his fore recited Petition, which copy thus followeth.</p>
            <q>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:165914:16"/>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="petition">
                        <head>To the Supreme Authority of this Nation, the Parliament of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth of <hi>England.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <head type="sub">The humble Petition of <hi>John Hedworth</hi> of <hi>Harraton</hi> in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Durham</hi> Eſquire:</head>
                        <opener>Sheweth,</opener>
                        <p>THAT in <hi>May</hi> 1650. about 60. head of your Petitioners Cattel were by order from the ſub-Commiſſioners for ſequeſtrations in the County of <hi>Durham,</hi> taken off your Petitioners grounds (where they were depaſtured) by ſome of Colonel <hi>Hackars</hi> Souldiers, under pretence that they were the goods of <hi>George Grey</hi> of <hi>Harraton</hi> Eſquire, your Petitioners Father-in-law, whoſe goods they would have taken under colour that he owed ſome monies to one <hi>Jackſon</hi> a <hi>Delinquent,</hi> that had compounded, and wanted ſome moneys to pay the latter moiety of his fine.</p>
                        <p>That your Petitioner being at that time in <hi>London,</hi> ſome of his friends demanded his cattel, of the ſaid Commiſſioners, and offered proof upon Oath, that they were your Petitioners goods; but they refuſed to take any proof, or to deliver the goods, but half ſtarved the cattel, and then ſould them at half their value.</p>
                        <p>That in <hi>Auguſt</hi> 1650. your Petitioner made his addreſs to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners for compounding for relief, and had an order from them to the ſaid ſub-Commiſſioners, that they ſhould certine the grounds of ſuch their proceedings to take away your Petitioners goods; but they made a return that they onely were the goods of the ſaid <hi>George Grey,</hi> without ſhewing the leaſt ground for that their opinion.</p>
                        <p>That your Petitioner thereupon did again the 5. of <hi>February</hi> 1650. move them about his ſaid goods, whereupon they ordered, that the Commiſſioners in the Country ſhould certifie within three weeks after notice of that order, all their proceedings touching the ſaid goods, which they would not do.</p>
                        <p>That your Petitioner thereupon, did the 28. of <hi>May</hi> laſt, again move the ſaid Commiſſioners for compounding, for ſatisfaction for his ſaid cattel, he being ready to prove them upon Oath to be his proper goods, and the ſaid ſub-Commiſſioners certifying no grounds whereupon they forcibly and moſt unjuſtly took them away, as the goods of the ſaid <hi>George Grey;</hi> and Oath was made that they were your Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioners goods, and thereupon the ſaid Commiſſioners for compoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, would onely order again, that the ſub-Commiſſioners ſhould cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie within ten daies after notice, what proofs they had, that the ſaid cattel were the goods of the ſaid <hi>George Grey;</hi> and your Petitioner was enforced to ſend 200. miles to ſerve the ſaid order, which was done ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly; yet the ſaid ſub-Commiſſioners would not obey the ſaid order, nor make any return: And your Petitioner was forced to his great expence, to cauſe one to come 200. miles to make oath of their diſobedience; yet the ſaid cattel alſo being fully proved by the Oaths of two ſufficient witneſſes before the ſaid Commiſſioners for compounding, to be the proper goods of your Petitioner: ſome of the ſaid Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners who over voted the reſt refuſe to order your Petitioner any ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, or to declare a permittance of your Petitioner to ſue for the ſame at Law, and would again ſend your Petitioner to attend the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of the ſaid ſub-Commiſſioners, who in ſeveral caſes of your Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oner,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:165914:17"/>have dealt moſt illegally and unjuſtly with him, and will obey no Orders.</p>
                        <p>That your Petitioners ſaid cattel being the whole ſtock upon his ground, the taking away the ſame and forcing your Petitioner to above a years attendance about them to no purpoſe, but vaſt expence and charge, and your Petitioner being young, and left much indebted by his father ſir <hi>John Hedworth,</hi> and not being able to ſtock his ground a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, and the reſerved rent of the colliery of <hi>Harraton,</hi> belonging to your Petitioner, being by the like unjuſt dealing of the ſaid ſub-Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners, and ſome of the chief Commiſſioners with <hi>Joſiah Primatt</hi> Leſſee to the ſaid colliery detained from him, it hath been almoſt the undoing of your Petitioner, and yet he is hopeleſs of any relief or juſtice at all from moſt of your Commiſſioners for compounding: whoſe particular inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt he hath too juſt cauſe to ſay, over-rules their judgments and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, theſe amongſt them that are willing to do him juſtice, (<hi>viz, M. Moyer, Mr. Barn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>rs,</hi> and <hi>Mr. Moor,</hi> being over-voted by the others.</p>
                        <p>That your Petitioner having been always well affected to the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and the ſaid <hi>George Grey</hi> having been a zealous actor and a Commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tee-man, and a great ſufferer for the Parliament; and in caſe he had ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the ſaid Delinquent <hi>Jack<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                                 <desc>••</desc>
                              </gap>n</hi> any money, the Delinquent having com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded for his whole eſtate, might and ought to have recovered the ſame at Law; ſo that the ſub-Commiſſioners had no power to take away the ſaid cattel, in caſe they had been the goods of the ſaid <hi>George Grey,</hi> as in the leaſt they were not.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>The premiſes duly conſidered: your Petitioner moſt humbly appeals to your honours as his laſt refuge, and craves the juſtice of you that ought to be and are the releevers of the diſtreſſed and oppreſſed, the maintainers of our Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties, freedoms, and proprieties; and therefore beſeecheth you, either of your ſelves to appoint a Committee of your own Houſe ſpeedily to examine the truth of his complaint, and to ſend for all papers at Haberdaſhers Hall or elſewhere that concerns the caſe, and to order and award him a full recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence for all his ſaid cattel and all his expences, and damages, which he judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth cannot amount to leſs then</hi> 500. l. <hi>and to do juſtice upon all your Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners oppreſſors for their Arbitrary and moſt unjuſt dealing with him; or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe, that it may be declared by you, that he is freely permitted to have his remedy a Law againſt the ſaid ſub-Commiſſioners, and their aſſiſtanets: whoſe unjuſt dealings with him, as in reference to his ſaid Cattle, is by true Copies of Affidavits hereunto annexed fully proved.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>And he ſhall pray, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> John Hedworth.</signed>
                        </closer>
                        <postscript>
                           <q>
                              <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                                 <body>
                                    <div type="affidavit">
                                       <p>
                                          <hi>JO'm Clifton</hi> of <hi>Gateſhead</hi> in the County of <hi>Durham</hi> Mercer maketh Oath, t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                             <desc>•</desc>
                                          </gap>at about the 17 of <hi>June</hi> 1650 Certain Soldiers belonging to Col. <hi>Ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                                <desc>•</desc>
                                             </gap>ker,</hi> did drive away from off the grounds of <hi>Harraton</hi> and <hi>Follensby</hi> in the ſaid County, between 50 and 60 head of cattel, as being the goods of Mr. <hi>George Gray,</hi> for certain Rents, pretended to be due from the ſaid Mr. <hi>Gray,</hi> to one Mr. <hi>Jackson</hi> a Delinquent, and indebted for his Compoſition money to the State: after which time this deponent with one Mr. <hi>Thomas Coſin</hi> of <hi>Newcaſtle,</hi> Draper, repaired to the Sub Commiſſioners for Seque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrations then ſitting at <hi>Durham,</hi> with a Petition from the wife of <hi>John Hed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worth</hi> of <hi>Harraton</hi> Eſquire (himſelf being at that time here in <hi>London</hi>) the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:165914:17"/>effect of which Petition was, that the ſaid goods were the proper goods of her husband; and that ſhe deſired the Commiſſioners then ſitting, would be pleaſed to give Order for the ſaid goods to be reſtored back to her; yet upon the engagement of this Deponent, and the ſaid Mr. <hi>Coſin</hi> to make good whatſoever ſhould be proved to be due from her husband to the State, which they refuſed; whereupon this deponent and the ſaid <hi>Coſin</hi> offered to enter bond, that within 14 days, upon anſwer from the ſaid <hi>John Hedworth</hi> (if any thing appeared due) we would pay it down: But the Commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners would have us to ingage to make good what was pre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                             <desc>•</desc>
                                          </gap>ended to be due from Mr. <hi>George Gray;</hi> which thing we refuſed, becauſe we knew the goods ſo driven were not the goods of Mr. <hi>Gray,</hi> but Mr. <hi>Hedworths,</hi> as this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent offered there 3 ſeveral times to depoſe; but the ſaid Commiſſioners re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed to take any proof that the ſaid goods were the onely proper goods of the ſaid <hi>John Hedworth.</hi> And this deponent further maketh Oath, that be certainly knoweth the goods at that time ſo driven, were really the goods of Mr <hi>Hedworth,</hi> and not Mr. <hi>Grays;</hi> which this deponent knoweth the better, becauſe he knoweth that the ſaid <hi>John Hedworth</hi> bought the ſame for a valuable conſideration without fraud or Truſt.</p>
                                       <closer>
                                          <dateline>
                                             <hi>Jur. coram commiſſariis</hi> 
                                             <date>9. <hi>April</hi> 1651.</date>
                                          </dateline>
                                          <signed>
                                             <list>
                                                <item>
                                                   <hi>R M.</hi>
                                                </item>
                                                <item>
                                                   <hi>John Clifton.</hi>
                                                </item>
                                             </list>
                                          </signed>
                                          <signed>
                                             <hi>Copia vera.</hi> T. Bayly.</signed>
                                       </closer>
                                    </div>
                                    <div type="affidavit">
                                       <p>
                                          <hi>Ralp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                                <desc>•</desc>
                                             </gap> Gray</hi> of <hi>Harraton</hi> in the County of <hi>Durham</hi> Gentleman, maketh Oath, that all the cattel (being be wixt 50 and 60 in number) driven off the grounds of <hi>Harraton,</hi> North <hi>Beddeck</hi> and <hi>Follemby,</hi> al in the County of <hi>Durham,</hi> by vertue of an Order of the Commiſſioners for Sequeſtration of the ſaid County of <hi>Durham,</hi> dated about <hi>June</hi> 1650. pretended thereby to be the cattle of <hi>George Gray</hi> of <hi>Harraton</hi> aforeſaid Eſquire, were the proper goods of <hi>John Hedworth</hi> Eſquire and others and not the goods of <hi>George Gray,</hi> and this he the more perſectly knoweth, for that this deponent was preſent at the bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                             <desc>•</desc>
                                          </gap>in making, betwixt the ſaid <hi>John Hedworth</hi> Eſquire, and the ſaid <hi>George Gray</hi> Eſquire, at the very time that the ſaid <hi>John Hedworth</hi> bought ſo many of the foreſaid cattle of the foreſaid <hi>George Gray,</hi> as did belong unto him, which were about 40 head, for which the ſaid <hi>John Hedworth</hi> was to pay a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout three hundred pounds to the ſaid <hi>George Gray;</hi> which bargain was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally made without fraud or truſt, and the cattel delivered thereupon into the poſſeſſion of <hi>John Hedworth,</hi> above ſix months before the foreſaid cattell were ſeiſed upon by order of the ſaid Commiſſioners. And this deponent further depoſeth, that amongſt the cattel aforeſaid were taken away at the ſame time (by vertue of the foreſaid Order) 3 or 4 of the cattel of one <hi>George Gray</hi> of <hi>Sudwick</hi> in the County aforeſaid.</p>
                                       <p>And he alſo depoſeth that the ſaid Eſquire <hi>Hedworth</hi> bought ſeveral of the foreſaid cattel that were taken away out of the foreſaid grounds, of his neighbours, viz. <hi>John Lax, Will Fenwick. Will. Hol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                                <desc>•</desc>
                                             </gap>.</hi> And he alſo depoſeth that the ſaid Eſquire <hi>Hedworth</hi> bred ſeveral of the foreſaid cattel, from the day of their being calved, and never was out of the reall poſſeſſion of them, till the time aforeſaid, that they were taken away as is before declared; and
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:165914:18"/>all this he the more perfectly knoweth, for that this deponent hath lived in the houſe with the ſaid Eſquire <hi>Hedworth,</hi> almoſt four years, and was by him admitted to a conſtant privity, to all or moſt of the actions and bargains of the ſaid Eſquire <hi>Hedworth,</hi> and in his abſence managed his affairs and bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs for him.</p>
                                       <closer>
                                          <dateline>
                                             <hi>Jur. Coram Commiſſariis</hi> 
                                             <date>9 <hi>July,</hi> 1651.</date>
                                          </dateline>
                                          <signed>Ralph Gray.</signed>
                                          <signed>R. M. <hi>vera Copia.</hi>
                                          </signed>
                                       </closer>
                                    </div>
                                 </body>
                              </floatingText>
                           </q>
                        </postscript>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>Theſe foregoing are the copies of 2 orders mentioned in the foregoing Petition, that were read in open Court, to prove the cattel taken away, to be the proper goods of <hi>John Hedworth</hi> Eſquire, and theſe two following papers are Copies of Affidavits produced in open Court, to prove the Sub-Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners ſlighting and contemning the Orders ſerved upon them from the Commiſſioners ſitting at Haberdaſhers Hall.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="affidavit">
                        <p>
                           <hi>John Hedworth</hi> of <hi>Harraton</hi> in the County of <hi>Durham</hi> Eſquire, maketh Oath, That upon the ſixth day of <hi>Auguſt</hi> 1650, being before the Commi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſioners for Sequeſtration at <hi>Durham,</hi> with an Order from the chief Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners at <hi>London,</hi> for putting him in poſſeſſion of his lands, which Order Sir <hi>Arthur</hi> Haſelrig would not ſuffer them to obey, but queſtioned this De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponent how he came in poſſeſſion of ſeveral of them; unto which this depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent made anſwer, that part of them he had and enjoyed by expiration of Leaſes, and part of others by Judgement at Law, and that he had ſeveral trials of that nature to come before the Judges at <hi>Durham</hi> the next aſſiſes, which were within a few days after: Upon which Sir <hi>Arthur Haſelrig</hi> told this deponent that he ſued for nothing but what belonged to the State; whereas the houſes and lands for which this deponent ſued, and upon which he had ſealed Leaſes of ejectment, and expected tryals, were his own In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance, and not ſequeſtred for his or any others delinquency; and that at the ſame time Sir <hi>Arthur Haſelrig</hi> turned him about in the Court, and openly commanded <hi>Col. Wren,</hi> that at the Judges coming to town, he ſhould repair unto them, and cauſe them not to ſuffer any proceedings in Court whatſoever, that had relation to any pretended lands of the ſaid deponent: By which means this deponent durſt not go on with his trials, whereby this deponent ſuſtained very much loſs and dammage. And this deponent further ſaith, that upon the 13 of <hi>February</hi> 1650. preſenting himſelf with his Councel before the ſaid Commiſſioners ſitting then at <hi>Durham,</hi> and that with a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Order from the chief Commiſſioners at <hi>London,</hi> for their obedience to the firſt which they refuſed, whereupon this deponents Councell, Mr. <hi>John Heath</hi> made the warrantableneſs of his cauſe to appear unto them, by vertue of that Order, and advice they laſt received from the chief Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners at <hi>London,</hi> whereunto Mr. <hi>Thomas Dallivale</hi> being one of the Sub-Commiſſioners then ſitting at <hi>Durham,</hi> anſwered and ſaid unto the ſaid de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponent and Mr. <hi>Heath</hi> his Councel, that notwithſtanding they had publick Orders preſented unto them, yet many times they received privat in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions to the contrary, or words to that effect.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <dateline>
                              <hi>Jur. Cotum Commiſſariis</hi> 
                              <date>
                                 <hi>July</hi> 2. 1651.</date>
                           </dateline>
                           <signed>John Hedworth.</signed>
                           <signed>R.M. <hi>vera Copia.</hi>
                           </signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                     <div type="affidavit">
                        <pb n="35" facs="tcp:165914:18"/>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Ralph Gray</hi> of <hi>Harraton</hi> in the Country of <hi>Durham</hi> Gentleman, maketh Oath, that upon the eleventh day of <hi>June</hi> laſt, he together with <hi>George Gray</hi> of <hi>Harraton</hi> Eſquire, did deliver unto the Commiſſioners for Sequeſtrations in the ſaid County, two Orders of the honourable the Commiſsioners for Compounding: the one bearing date the 23 of <hi>May</hi> 1651. concerning the examination of witneſſes in the Caſe of <hi>George Gray</hi> of <hi>Harraton</hi> aforeſaid Eſquire, and to return the examinations in five weeks, from the ſaid 25. of <hi>May:</hi> and the other bearing date the 28 of <hi>May</hi> 1651. whereby the ſaid Commiſſioners were ordered to ſend up to the ſaid Commiſſioners for Compounding, the proofes upon Oath; whereupon they judged the cattel taken from <hi>John Hedworth</hi> of <hi>Harraton</hi> Eſquire, to be the cattell of <hi>George Gray</hi> Eſquire, and to examine witneſſes on both ſides if deſired, and to make return therof within ten dayes after notice of the ſaid order; and both the ſaid Orders were entred in the Book of the ſaid Commiſſioners for Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtrations. And he further maketh Oath, that upon ths ſaid eleventh day of <hi>June</hi> laſt, he together with the ſaid <hi>George Gray,</hi> deſired the ſaid Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſionerss for Sequeſtrations, that in obedience to both the ſaid Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, they would ſet a time to examine witneſſes in both the ſaid ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes; but they could not prevail with them to ſet any time: and this depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent did upon the eighteenth day of <hi>June</hi> laſt, together with the ſaid <hi>George Gray</hi> again attend the ſaid Commiſſioners for Sequeſtrations, to appoint a time to examine witneſſes according to the two Orders a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid, that he delivered to them; but they could not prevail with them to appoint any time, but Maſter <hi>Dalavall,</hi> one of them, ſaid, they knew what they had to do; ſo that this deponent and the ſaid <hi>George Gray</hi> waited for their obedience to the ſaid Order untill the time li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited in the ſaid Order for a return from the ſaid commiſſioners for Seque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrations in the ſaid County, was elapſed, and they would do nothing therein.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <dateline>
                              <hi>Jur. Coram Commiſſariis</hi> 
                              <date>9. <hi>July</hi> 1651.</date>
                           </dateline>
                           <signed>Ralph Gray.</signed>
                           <signed>R. M. <hi>Vera copia.</hi>
                           </signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                     <div type="affidavit">
                        <head>Here followeth the Copy of a third Affidavit of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                           <hi>George Gray</hi>'s to prove the goods to be <hi>John Hedworth</hi>'s Eſquire.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>George Gray</hi> of <hi>Harraton</hi> in the County of <hi>Durham</hi> Gentleman, aged ſix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty eight years or thereabouts, maketh Oath, That whereas by a Certifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate from the Commiſsioners for Sequeſtrations in the County of <hi>Dur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> dated 14 <hi>Novembris</hi> 1650. it is alledged that upon an Order made by the ſaid Commiſsioners dated <hi>March</hi> 19, 1649. whereby Colonel <hi>Hacker</hi> was Authorized to diſtrein the goods of this deponent for ſome ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rears of Rents, pretended to be due by this deponent to one <hi>John Jakson</hi> a delinquent, that thereupon this deponent (upon or about the time of the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the aboveſaid Order) did cunningly and fraudulently pretend that he had aſſigned the cattell ſo diſtreined unto <hi>John Hedworth</hi> Eſquire, this deponents ſon in law, and that this was done in colour to defraud the State, to whom the ſaid Rents were due, as is alledged in the ſaid Certifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate. Now this deponent depoſeth and ſaith, That the goods, nor any of
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:165914:19"/>them ſo taken or diſtreined by the Order of the ſaid Commiſſioners, upon the grounds at <hi>Harraton</hi> or thereabout (pretended to be the goods of this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponent) were not at the time of the ſaid diſtreſſe, nor had been for the ſpace of twelve months before that time, any of this deponents goods, neither had this deponent any title or intereſt in any of them; but that the ſaid cattell were moſt of them really the proper goods of the ſaid <hi>John Hedworth</hi> Eſquire, and ſome of them belonged to ſome other neighbours, who never yet got them again to this deponents know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <dateline>
                              <hi>Jur. Coram Commiſſariis</hi> 
                              <date>9. <hi>April</hi> 1651.</date>
                           </dateline>
                           <signed>George Gray.</signed>
                           <signed>R. M. <hi>Vera copia.</hi>
                           </signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>Now laying theſe few things together, (which yet are but a part of what I have to complain of) let me appeale to your conſciences (as not long ſince I did at your open B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>) whether Sir <hi>Arthur Haſelrig,</hi> and his under Commiſſioners, or petty ſlaves in the Countrey, have not dealt worſe with us then ever wicked <hi>Ahab</hi> dealt with poor <hi>Naboth,</hi> who ſcorned to take away his vineyard from him, before he had proffered him a better for it, or the value in money? but Sir <hi>Arthur</hi> &amp;c. hath taken away our poffeſſion by force and violence, without ſo much as ever proffering us one peny of conſideration therefore, or ever ſo much as ſetting up a man of ſtraw by way of title againſt us; and hath dealt with us ſo, that as I then told you, ſo I aver now, it had been a happineſs for us when we fell into Sir <hi>Arthur's</hi> hands, we had fallen into the hands of theeves and robbers upon the high way; for then we could have raiſed the hue and cry after them, and have had ſome ſport (at leaſt) for our money and goods; or if it had been done in the day time, we could at law have recovered our money of the Hundred where the robbery was committed; whereas now, God knows, we are by Sir <hi>Arthur,</hi> (<hi>Strafford</hi> like) expreſly denied the benefit of the Law, our inheritance and birthright; and by you, whom the Parliament hath appointed in all ſuch caſes, as now I complain of, to do us juſtice and right, denied all the rules of juſtice, conſcience, and equity; and by you our blood-ſuck'd, and expoſed to pining by little and little, and made by you ten times worſe, and not better, by a conſtant attendance upon you for your Orders, and then when they are got to ride above 200 miles to ſerve them in the Countrey, and there dance attendance for their anſwers; and then poſt up above 200. miles again to make Affidavit of the ſerving of them, and then to wait up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on you till your leiſure pleaſeth to vouchſafe to be told of your Under-Commiſſioners contempts of your publick Orders, upon the private in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions you ſend them; and then upon the motion to ſtruggle for a new Order, like horſes in a mill, you will juſt go round, and give only in effect what was in the former, after a moneths attendance to our vaſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence, and then make us ſtay a week, or ten dayes ſometimes, before you will vouchſafe to ſet four of your hands to it, ſome of your four ſelves ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving got a trick to carp and pick quarrels at any orders you like not, though made according to the publick Vote that you are at the debate of; yea ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, when three hands are to an Order, a fourth of you will except againſt
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:165914:19"/>it, and make a new one to be drawn; and then in caſe of rubs when it comes to be ſpoken unto, an anſwer is ready, that you are full of buſineſſe, and things muſt come in courſe: and ſo there is delay upon delay <hi>ad inſini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum;</hi> by means of which your Court is become a greater torment and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory than the Pope's.</p>
            <p>Nay, this is not all, for as I once averr'd at your Bar, ſo I do the ſame now, that by Sir <hi>Arthur's</hi> dealing (ſo arbitrarily and tyrannically) with us, to rob us of our Lands, Goods, Eſtates, and Inheritances at his will and pleaſure, he commits higher treaſon then <hi>Strafford</hi> did, (if deſtruction and levelling of properties, ſubverſion of laws, and exerciſing of an arbitrary tyrannicall power be treaſon.) For alas! poor <hi>Strafford</hi> did what he did, to <hi>Richard</hi> Earl of <hi>Corck,</hi> and to the Lord <hi>Mount Norris,</hi> and to <hi>Thomas</hi> Lord <hi>Dillon,</hi> and to <hi>Adam</hi> Viſcount <hi>Loftus,</hi> and to <hi>George</hi> Earl of <hi>Kildare,</hi> &amp;c. in a Prerogative time, when there was little hopes or expectation of ſeeing a Parliament to redreſſe the peoples grievances; and yet for all that <hi>Strafford</hi> in thoſe times did, he had the then common received countenance of Authority, <hi>viz.</hi> the Kings Commiſſions, who was then commonly reputed and ſtiled the Fountain of Law and Juſtice. But Sir <hi>Arthur Haſlerig</hi> and his Aſſociats hath deſtroyed and levelled our proprieties, and in our caſe ſubverted the Laws and Liberties of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, and exerciſed an arbitrary and tyrannicall power over us, againſt and without law; and that after he himſelf was one of the Judges to condemn <hi>Strafford,</hi> as a Traitor, to have his head chop'd off for the like or leſſe things; and during the ſitting of a Parliament, the people of Englands hopes for the redreſſe of all their grievances, hath this been done by him; nay, after the Parliament hath raiſed and maintained a bloody War for the preſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the lawes, proprieties and liberties of the people: and after the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament hath chop'd off the Kings head for violation of the laws and liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of England; and after the Parliament hath forc'd the people to take many Oathes, and after themſelves have put forth many Declarations to maintain the lawes and liberties of <hi>England,</hi> with all things incident and belonging to the lives, liberties and properties of the people, hath Sir <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thur Haſterig</hi> done this tranſcendent wickedneſſe, without any ſhadow or colour from Order, Ordinances, or Act of Parliament; to the unſufferable and unſpeakable indignity and diſhonour of the Parliament, and to the apparant hazard of their ruine and deſtruction, by alienating (as much as in him lyes) the peoples hearts and affections from them; yea, the hearts of their cordialleſt friends. And therefore I hope in due time to ſee the ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grieved, oppreſſed, and ſuffering people in the four Northern Counties, that have ſuffered by him and his Officers, as one man petition the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to have their juſt complaints againſt him, and upon proof thereof to confiſcate his vaſt, ſuddenly but ill got eſtate, to make them ſatisfaction for the wrongs he hath done them; and for the overplus of his eſtate, to beſtow it upon the four Northern waſted and oppreſſed Counties, to be kept as an annuall revenue to help to pay their publick Taxes; for it is impoſſible that ſo vaſt an eſtate, as in ſo ſhort a time he hath got his together, ſhould be come by honeſtly and juſtly: And in <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth's time it was
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:165914:20"/>eſteemed an high crime in Cardinal <hi>Wolſey</hi> and his ſervants to grow ſo rich of a ſudden; as appears by the Articles preferred againſt him to the King, by the then Lords of the privie Councel, recorded in the fourth part of the Lord <hi>Cook's Inſtitutes, fol.</hi> 89. 90. 91. 92. 95. See Article 21. 22. and in Article 44. Their words are, <q>That by his unſatiable avarice, and ravenous appetite to have riches and treaſure without meaſure, he hath ſo grievouſly oppreſſed your poor ſubjects with ſo manifold crafts of bribery and extortion, that the Common-wealth of this your Graces Realm is thereby greatly decayed and impoveriſhed. And alſo his cruelty, iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, affection and partiality hath ſubverted the due courſe and order of your Graces Laws, to the undoing of a great number of your loving people: And therefore they humbly pray of the King, That ſuch a puniſhment may be inflicted upon him, as may be to the terrible example of others, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware ſo to offend your Grace, and your Lawes hereafter.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Gentlemen, I might further go on to illuſtrate, and ſhew the further de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes of Sir <hi>Arthur</hi> to undermine and ruine my Family; but this Epiſtle is ſwell'd already to a greater bigneſs then I intended, and my ſhortneſſe of time by reaſon of an intended long journey, will not permit me further at large to proceed; and therefore I ſhall reſerve what is behinde for ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther encounter, or a ſecond part to the ſame tune; where I ſhall pretty fully open the great myſtery and deſigne of Sir ARTHUR by his ſpecious pretences to the Parliament, to get them to overthrow all the old Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittees of Sequeſtration. In ſhort, he could never in the Northern parts have put out all thoſe faithfull men that would never bow their knees to <hi>Baal</hi> (I mean, his will and pleaſure) if he had not accompliſh'd that, and with his huge zealous long ſpeeches and pretences have blinded the Houſe, to make them judg him a fit man to be one of the two to name the ſeven principall Commiſſioners; amongſt which, though there was a mixture of honeſt men, yet the major part of you being his vaſſals, hee had there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by an opportunity to get you to place in to be under-Commiſſioners in the North, the baſeſt of men, that would ſoly captivate their reaſons and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences to his luſt and will; and there being in that County enough of all the three ſizes, that are fit for a tyrants uſe, <hi>viz.</hi> fools, knaves, or beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, he in the County of <hi>Durham,</hi> as I lately told you at your Barrs, having put us in two men to govern our Country, <hi>viz.</hi> Collonel <hi>Fran. Wren,</hi> and Maſter <hi>Thomas Dalavall,</hi> that by reaſon of their baſeneſs are fit for nothing but to be kick'd out of a Common-wealth; for beſides their groſs partiality and injuſtice in their places, the one of them, <hi>viz.</hi> Col. <hi>Wren</hi> was, as I then told you, caſheered at the head of his army or Regimant, at his firſt expediti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on into Scotland for the baſeſt plundering fellow that ever march'd at the heeles of a man of honour; and this I told you to be true and I would make it good: and now I further tel you, that at the Generals coming back for En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland, at <hi>Barnard</hi> Caſtle in the County of <hi>Durham</hi> he was pleaſed to give un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to my Father, and ſome other well affected Gantlemen, a narrative of his baſenes, and the danger by his unworthy cariage he put his army into: and for the other, <hi>viz.</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Tho. Dalavall,</hi> it was well known he was a conſtant adhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er to, and liver in the Earle of New-caſtles quarters, and never in times
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:165914:20"/>by paſt ſo much as reputed a private well wiſher to the Parliameur or their welfare, but rather ſtrongly judged to be a commiſſionated Captain for the Earl of <hi>Newcaſtle</hi> in the Garriſon of <hi>Newcaſtle;</hi> and therefore ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, it may be, guilt enough in his own conſcience, and peradventure ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently known to Sir <hi>Arthur,</hi> he is a fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>man for him to hold a rod over his ſhoulders, thereby right or wrong to do as he would have him, as that Jury of Cavaliers did for Sir <hi>Arthur</hi> in one Maſter <hi>Fenwicks</hi> caſe, about ſeven miles from <hi>Newcaſtle,</hi> who at my laſt being in the North, came to my brother <hi>Gors</hi> to me, and freely told me to this effect, that Sir <hi>Arthur</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a mind to his land (<hi>Ahab</hi> like) having the High-Sheriffe and the Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der-Sheriffe at his beck and command, whom he cauſed to pannell a Jury of Delinquents to paſſe upon it, who being Maſter <hi>Fenwicks</hi> Neighbours, came all, or the moſt part to him, and told him they were his neighbours, and in their conſciences knew well enough he had a good right and title to his land; but, ſaid they, Maſter <hi>Fenwick,</hi> you know we have been in enmity againſt the State, and under the laſh and indignation of Sir <hi>Arthur</hi> to deſtroy us at his will and pleaſure, with our wives, and children, and he hath put us on purpoſe upon your Jury, and been with us, &amp;c. and we muſt either go againſt our conſciences, and do as he will have us to find your land for him, or elſe you know he will deſtroy both us, our wives, and children, and therefore ſay they to him, We beg of you for Gods ſake to adviſe with your Councell to finde out ſome clauſe in the Law to except againſt us, having been Cavaliers, as unfit to be of your Jury, or elſe if you get us not put off, we muſt find againſt you, although it be againſt our owne knowledge and conſcience.</p>
            <p>But the man fully knowing the integrity of his cauſe, and believing they knew it as well as himſelf, he ſaid, If they would damn their ſouls let them; and ſo was overthrowne, and now is like, as he himſelf told me and others, totally thereby to be ruined. And the truth of it is, Sir <hi>Arthur</hi> can in our County find no man ſo fit for his purpoſe, as theſe that have guilt enough upon their ſhoulders; and therefore it is that he hath under him Maſter <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Shadford</hi> for our high Sheriffe, a ſtrongly reputed Cavalier in both the warrs, and approved one in the firſt, but yet never ſequeſtred. But beſides, Sir <hi>Arthur</hi> hath not onely the command over our bodies and eſtates there, but alſo he is turned the Arch-biſhop of our ſoules, having Maſter <hi>Wels</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der him for his officiating Biſhop or commiſſary, by whom he hath almoſt made ſure of all the Pulpits and tithes in the country: So that truly and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geniouſly, Sir <hi>Arthur Haſlerig</hi> there hath reduced us to that nighneſſe of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finity to French Peaſants, that can call nothing they buy or work for their own, longer then their Lords and Maſters pleaſe to let them injoy it; that in good earneſt, I ſpeak it from my very ſoul and conſcience, that I verily be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve, if I, or ſome body elſe ſhould not riſe up againſt him, to indeavour to bring him to a juſt account for his unjuſt actions, all the land that I have in that country, which the Parliament (as the price of my blood, for my Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copal and Star-chamber ſorrows) have (by the Honourable and Noble mediation of the preſent Lord Generall) ſettled upon me and my heires, in one year or two more, would not be (as yet I will juſtifie it, it hath not been) worth unto me one groat, the tenants rebelling both againſt the
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:165914:21"/>State and me, and telling my agents they have powerfull backers: and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it is the price of my blood, and the product of ſo many piercing ſorrows as I have undergone for it, I am reſolved through the ſtrength of God, that never a private or particular man in <hi>England</hi> ſhall deprive me of it, or of the priviledges that belong unto me by it, unleſs his ſword be ſo long and ſtrong that it is able to cut mine in peices, and the hand that holds it, and alſo the tongue that uſeth to plead cheerfully without amazement for my life and liberty.</p>
            <p>There is much more of your juggling and unjuſt dealing about my Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle <hi>George</hi>'s delinquency behind, in your ſending down private commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, to examine witneſſes againſt him, without his knowledge, with ſuch inſtructions as that you are ſo aſhamed to have ſeen, that when I bid Maſter <hi>Baily</hi> your clark five peices of gold to let Maſter <hi>Hugh Peters</hi> then with us, to read them, or twenty peices to give me a copy of them, he ingeniouſly told Maſter <hi>Peters</hi> and my ſelf, he durſt not: and being ask'd by him, Why? he was by his Maſters commanded to the contrary; and being ask'd by which of them, he told us, he durſt not tell us, but they ſat at the table, and if he pleaſ'd, he might go and diſcourſe with themſelves, and ſee if he could find it out himſelf; for truly he was but a ſervant and durſt ſay no more, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore deſired to be preſt no further. Upon which Maſter <hi>Peters</hi> with open mouth coming to the table, cryed ſhame of you to the purpoſe: and you may remember honeſt Maſter <hi>Moyer</hi> told you he knew not of it, nor had no fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger in it, and it was an abominable ſhame any ſuch thing ſhould be done, and promiſed me a copy of it; but to this day I could never ſet my eyes upon it. But the full diſcourſing of this with much more muſt remaine for a ſecond part. And ſo at preſent I bid you farwel, and reſt,</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>From my houſe without Ludgate, at the end of the old Baily,</hi> 
                  <date>this 30. <hi>July.</hi> 1651.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>JOHN LILBURNE, now as honeſt as ever, and as ready to juſtifie the eſentiall ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of all here written with his life and fortune as ever he was to do any a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in the world.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <head>POSTSCRIPT.</head>
            <p>Gentlemen, Your intereſt with Sir <hi>Arthurs</hi> may be ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry great, and to do me a miſchief to the purpoſe, you may incenſe the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againſt me to deſtroy me for medling with them; but truly, I hope, I have been too wiſe for you, by totally (I hope) avoyding the medling with them in the leaſt. And I hope, ſeeing lately they have taught me ſuch a piece of gallant juſtice in the Lord <hi>Howards</hi> caſe, they wil not be offended at me for faithfully indeavouring to prepare for them a greater offender then he, <hi>viz.</hi> Sir <hi>Arthur Haſelrig:</hi> and I hope, I ſtand now as right in the eye of the Parliament in generall, as any man in England, having of late done all ſuch actions in reſpect and obedience to them that is fitting for a wiſe man, or a man of conſcience or honour to do, to take off all their jealouſies from him, that I go not about in the leaſt to diſturb their peace and quietnes, but mind and deſire the tranquility of this Common-wealth in my little ſphere, as much as they do in their great. And ſo I remain.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Auguſt</hi> 2. 1651.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>The ſame <hi>John Lilburne,</hi> I uſed to be.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
